<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new handling of the planisphere diuided into three sections. In the first is a plaine and sensible explication of the circles of the sphere, and such termes as appertaine vnto the doctrine de primo mobili ... The second sheweth how vpon any plaine ... hauing one circle diuided into degrees, and crossed vvith tvvo diameters at right angles, most conclusions of the astrolabe may for all latitudes or countries be readily and exactly performed onely vvith ruler and compasses. In the third, being a supplement organicall, is contained the making of certaine easie instruments for the perfecter working the former conclusions, as to know what degrees and minutes be in any circumference giuen ... Pleasant and profitable generally for all men, but especially such as vvould get handines in vsing the ruler and compasse ... vvithout being at the charge of costly instruments. Inuented for the most part, and first published in English by Thomas Olyuer.</title>
            <author>Oliver, Thomas, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13856</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13856)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1147:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new handling of the planisphere diuided into three sections. In the first is a plaine and sensible explication of the circles of the sphere, and such termes as appertaine vnto the doctrine de primo mobili ... The second sheweth how vpon any plaine ... hauing one circle diuided into degrees, and crossed vvith tvvo diameters at right angles, most conclusions of the astrolabe may for all latitudes or countries be readily and exactly performed onely vvith ruler and compasses. In the third, being a supplement organicall, is contained the making of certaine easie instruments for the perfecter working the former conclusions, as to know what degrees and minutes be in any circumference giuen ... Pleasant and profitable generally for all men, but especially such as vvould get handines in vsing the ruler and compasse ... vvithout being at the charge of costly instruments. Inuented for the most part, and first published in English by Thomas Olyuer.</title>
                  <author>Oliver, Thomas, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>79, 82-99, [3] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston, for Simon Waterson and Rafe Iacson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf contains an illustration intended to cancel that on p. 35.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Planispheres --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW HAND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING OF THE PLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISPHERE, DIVIDED into three Sections.</p>
            <p>IN THE FIRST IS A PLAINE AND ſenſible explication of the circles of the Sphere, and ſuch termes as appertaine vnto the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <hi>de primo mobili;</hi> after a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode not heretofore vſed in any language.</p>
            <p>THE SECOND SHEWETH HOW VPON any plaine, being Paper, Paſtboord, or a Latten plate, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing one circle diuided into degrees, and croſſed vvith tvvo Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters at right angles, moſt Concluſions of the Astrolabe may for all Latitudes or Countries be readily and exactly performed onely vvith Ruler and Compaſſes.</p>
            <p>IN THE THIRD, BEING A SVPPLEMENT OR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganicall, is contained the making of certaine eaſie inſtruments for the perfecter working the former Concluſions, as to know what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and minutes be in any circumference giuen, with other neceſſarie matters about the Meridian line and the height of the Pole.</p>
            <p>Pleaſant and profitable generally for all men, but eſpecially ſuch as vvould get handines in vſing the Ruler and Compaſſe, and deſire to reape the fruite of Aſtronomicall and Geographicall documents, vvithout being at the charge of coſtly Inſtruments.</p>
            <p>Inuented for the moſt part, and firſt publiſhed in Engliſh by THOMAS OLYVER.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KYNGSTON, for <hi>Simon Waterſon</hi> and <hi>Rafe Iacſon.</hi> 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL SIR IOHN PETER KNIGHT, at Thornedon in Eſſex.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing well (right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) after the diſpatch of much weighty buſines, which for the good of others you willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vndertake, and, by report of the ſhire, with very great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and all vprightnes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that as it were for your recreation, you peruſed often bookes of Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie: ſome while ſince I ſent the manner how three or foure problemes Geographicall might bee wrought vpon a plaine with Ruler and Compaſſe only. At my leiſure afterward taking that ſubiect in hand againe, I followed it ſo farre, that I deuiſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the like way to handle moſt concluſions of the Aſtrolabe, or problems Aſtronomicall concerning the <hi>Primum mobile.</hi> When I had almoſt brought my purpoſe to effect, it was my chaunce to light vpon <hi>Clauius</hi> his Aſtrolabe, where I found as much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and performed euen by <hi>Ptolomeis Analomma,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13856:3"/>the very modell of <hi>Iohannes de Roias</hi> his Planiſphere, as learned <hi>Guidus Vbaldus</hi> hath fully proued, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ground vpon which I haue framed much of my worke. Notwithſtanding, perceiuing (as by compariſon euery one may ſee) that except the 5. and 28. taken out of <hi>Manrolycus,</hi> the 14. and 23. out of <hi>Commandine</hi> and <hi>Vbaldus,</hi> my conſtructions were very farre differing from <hi>Clauius,</hi> amending thoſe defects which <hi>Gemma</hi> noteth in <hi>Roias</hi> his worke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides taking the matter to be commodious, and not vnpleaſant for trauellers, and all ſuch in generall as delight in Aſtronomicall and Geographicall deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I ſet light the reproachfull name of an Engliſh Scribler, and tooke courage by publiſhing it to the view of the world, to hazard my ſelfe to euery rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders cenſuring. Vpon this reſolution I am bold to vſe your Worſhips name in the front of this booke, teſtifying therby the earneſt and vnfained affection which I beare, and long haue borne both to you and yours: in regard whereof making no doubt, but that this little mite ſhall be gently accepted, with remembrance of my dutie to your Worſhip I take my leaue. S. <hi>Edmunds Bury</hi> in Suffolke, 6. Ian. 1600. after our Engliſh accompt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all dutie moſt affectionate, <hi>THOMAS OLIVER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing the matters here entreated of admit no eloquence, but muſt in plaine attire be ſimply offered to the view, though I could (gentle Reader) I would not flouriſh with thee, in pleading for my ſelfe or this treatiſe: therefore referring all to thy friendly cenſure, I will ſpend this voide paper in aduertiſements for the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and eaſier performing of that which is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            <p>The fitteſt matter, whereupon you may worke theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions following, will be a plate of braſſe, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, Pritchet, Pointer or Steele, wherewith you muſt draw your lines, would be either of the ſame ſubſtance, or els Iron rather than Steele: for if you make not your ſtrokes verie deepe, by rubbing the plate with a wet Pumice, you may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily take all out when you will, and thereby alſo tarriſh or darken it in ſuch ſort, that you may preſently at your eaſe, and very exactly draw, and worke vpon it againe.</p>
            <p>When you begin to practiſe, it will helpe very much to work one concluſion by it ſelfe, and to note the lines, as you draw them, with the characters, that are named in the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar conſtruction: but when you are ſomething perfect, this ſhall not neede.</p>
            <p>You may alſo, hauing a quadrant diuided, make any paper ſerue the turne for theſe purpoſes. Opening your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the diſtance of 60. degrees, at that diſtance diſcribe a circle, and ſubtending foure times in it a line equall to that line, which ſubtendeth the quadrants circumference,
<pb facs="tcp:13856:4"/>if you ioyne the oppoſite points, it ſhall be croſſed with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular Diameters, then transferring the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences giuen or found from the quadrant to the circle, or from the circle to the quadrant, you may finde the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of any circumference as well, as though your circle were diuided into degrees.</p>
            <p>Where you deſire exactnes, you muſt reſt neither on this way, nor on the inſtrument in the beginning of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſection, but vſe that quadrant which you are taught to make in the beginning of the third ſection, by it you may know the iuſt content of any giuen circumference in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and minutes exactly, and let this be a generall war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for all concluſions.</p>
            <p>I haue barely ſet downe the conſtructions without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, as the fitteſt for their capacities, whoſe good I ſpecially aime at: yet is there nothing here propounded that hath not demonstratiuely been examined: and for experimentall triall the working by theſe concluſions may be compared with tables calculated for the ſame purpoſe, which, if handines and diligence be vſed, will agree.</p>
            <p>Since my writing of the ſecond ſection, I haue found how the concluſions therein omitted may bee perfectly wrought without the helpe of any <hi>Elleipſis,</hi> and all contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the compaſſe of the limbe: but at this time I thought not good to adde them.</p>
            <p>Thus much (gentle Reader) I thought meete thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be aduertiſed of: and ſo deſiring thee to pardon the eſcapes of my penne, if thou meeteſt with any, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thee and thy honeſt ſtudies to our Lords holie direction.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine THOMAS OLYVER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13856:4"/>
            <head>A new handling of the <hi>Planisphere.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>THE FIRST SECTION, WHERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is contained a plaine and ſenſible declaration of the circles of the Sphere, and the termes vſed in the doctrine <hi>de primo mobili,</hi> after another Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode than is yet in any other language.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE circles of the Sphere haue more than once alreadie bin writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of in Engliſh: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I think it wil not be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted labour loſt, though it were only for the better vnderſtanding of the concluſions following, here to handle them againe as princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the beginning of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Ptolomey</hi> for proofe of ſome matters here propounded, haue vſed many exquiſite arguments, which I meane not to proſecute, but hoping from the teſtimonie of ſenſe in ſuch manner to deduce the poſitions, that any meane capacitie may haue ſo reaſonable a conceit of them, that with probabilitie they may eaſily be admitted, I will referre their exact and more ſubtile demonſtration, with the reproofe of ſuch as impugne them, to ſome others hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or to ſome other place. Therefore requiring firſt the reader not to caſt vntimely doubts, nor haſtily to iudge of any part by it ſelfe, before he hath conſidered, and in ſome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13856:5"/>manner vnderſtood the whole diſcourſe, I will according to <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his counſell begin with the notableſt and eaſieſt things. Whoſoeuer doth but caſt vp his eyes vnto heauen, preſently perceiueth that it compaſſeth him round about in manner of halfe a globe or an Hemiſphere: and if he ſtand vpon ſome high place, or be at Sea farre from land, where nothing can be ſéene but water and the Skie, his eye, if he turne himſelfe about, will repreſent vnto him at the loweſt bounds or limits, which he ſeeth, the faſhion of a circle, vpon whoſe plaine, as vpon a baſe, this viſible Hemiſphere ſeemeth to be placed: therefore that Circle was firſt in Gréeke, and is now commonly in Engliſh called the Horizon, that is to ſay, bounding or limiting, <hi>vz.</hi> the compaſſe of your ſight. The largenes of this Circle, euen as it falleth vnder view, is of ſo great a compaſſe, as you neede not reſtraine the center thereof, according to the preciſe Mathematicall definition, to one determinate, exquiſite, indiuiſible, and very poynt, or pricke, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſenſible error, as your eye will plainly teſtifie, any one at pleaſure may bee taken in the place where you ſtand. From a center ſo taken, if there be, or be imagined, a plumbe line or line perpendicular to the plaine of the Horizon extended vnto the heauen, the place, which there it toucheth, is commonly called by an Arabian name the Zenith, being in truth the pole of the Horizon, and the line it ſelfe his Axis. By this Axis, and any lines croſſing it, if plainnes be euery way exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded reaching vnto heauen, they marke out their circumferences, or ſemicircles, cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one another in the Zenith: but in the Horizon their ſections are right lines, cutting one another in his center. Thoſe circles are named Azimutes, and are imagined by Aſtronomers to be cut by other circles parallel to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, which they terme Alinicantars and circles of Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, becauſe the portion of the Azimute, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Horizon and the Parallel, ſheweth how his aboue the Horizon that poynt of the Parallel is, by which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13856:5"/>the Azimute paſſeth. Furthermore, in a cléere night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the bright ſhining Starres, you ſhall euidently perceiue how they change their places continually, ſome to riſe and ſhew themſelues, other to goe downe vnder the Horizon, and to be hidden from your ſight, onely if you place your ſelfe ſo, that your right hand be towards their riſing, and your left hand toward their going downe, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king right foorth, and ſomewhat vpward, you ſhall behold certen Starres, which are all times of the night to bée ſeene, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of constallations</figDesc>
                     <p>Charles Wayne.</p>
                     <p>pole star.</p>
                     <p>Little Beare</p>
                  </figure>
go down; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ſome of which pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced after this faſhion, there is one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Pole ſtar, which being the laſt in the tayle of the conſtellation called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> little Beare, lyeth in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly as it were in a right line, with thoſe two in the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermoſt whéeles of Charles his wayne. This Starre ſeemeth little or nothing to remoue out of his place, and indeede not farre from it there is a poynt, or pricke, which remaineth in one and the ſame place alwaies immoueable. The Azimute paſſing by the Horizons Axis, and a right line drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this immoueable point, or the pole ſtarre, is properly called the Meridian circle; the common ſection of it and the Horizon, being a right line, is the Meridian line, or the line of North and South; the right line, which croſſeth this Meridian line at right angles in the center of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13856:6"/>the Horizon, is called the line of true Eaſt, and true Weſt, or ſimply the line of Eaſt and Weſt, which poynts the ends thereof extended directly fall vpon. The Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute ſtanding vpon this line, <hi>Ioannes de Roias,</hi> &amp; others, ſpecially ſuch as write of Dyalling, as it were for digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and preheminence, doe call the Verticall circle: which name being common to all Azimutes, becauſe they paſſe by the Zenith, in Latin called <hi>Vertex.</hi> or <hi>punctum eregione verticis:</hi> for a diſtinction <hi>Gemma Froſius</hi> hath named it the Circle of the Eaſt. The other Azimutes haue no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per names, but are meaſured or determined in the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons circumference. That, and ſo likewiſe all other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Aſtronomers doe imagine to be diuided into <hi>360.</hi> equall parts, which they name degrées, that is to ſay, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie quarter or quadrant into <hi>90.</hi> degrees: euery degrée they further diuide into <hi>60.</hi> minutes, euery minute into <hi>60.</hi> ſeconds, euery ſecond into <hi>60.</hi> thirds, and ſo continue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vnto tenths, and may goe further if they will. By theſe degrees, minutes, &amp;c. which are betwéene that point, where any Azimute cutteth the Horizon, and the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian line, or the line of Eaſt and Weſt, the Azimute is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, aſſigned, or ſaid to be giuen. Vpon the points where the Verticall circle cutteth the Horizon, which poynts are the true poles of the Meridian, and the preciſe Eaſt and Weſt, if by often and diligent viewing you ſhall ſee two Starres, the one in the Eaſt, and the other at the ſame time right againſt it in the Weſt, in winter time euen in one night, you may behold that which is in the Eaſt firſt aſcending, and then againe deſcending at length to come into the Weſt, and that which was in the Weſt being till that time hidden from your ſight, then to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare againe riſing in the Eaſt: all this while continually the like ſhape of an Hemiſphere being ſtill repreſented to your eye, without any chaunge or alteration, whereby you may gather the heauen to bee a perfect Globe, or Sphere, hauing that part vnder the Horizon equall and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13856:6"/>like to that which you ſée aboue it, and that the place where you ſtand is the very center thereof. A line drawne from the pole Starre, or rather from the poynt immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able before mentioned, called the Articke, or North pole, a line (I ſay) drawne, or imagined to be drawne from that poynt to the place of your ſtanding, is called the Aris of the world, and extended to the other ſide of the celeſtiall Sphere, which is vnder vs, falleth there vpon the South or Antarcticke pole, which in theſe our countries neuer appeareth. Theſe things, being but a little héedily conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, be ſo manifeſt and apparant, that neither example nor figure is greatly requiſite for the perfect vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them: yet in this beginning to remoue all difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to make euery thing as plaine as may be, doe thus much: In ſome plaine ground, or rather vpon a poſte, or ſtone, or ſome ſuch like thing made exactly ſmooth, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very flat, without any manner of leaning or decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which you muſt warily and diligently trie by your leuel, and your plumbe line, take the center A, vpon which deſcribe a circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> repreſenting the Horizon, whoſe circumference you may diuide, or imagine onely to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into degrées, and from <hi>A,</hi> the center thereof, erect a Stéele or wier, ſtanding plumbe vpright, or perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to the flat of the circle <hi>A B C D,</hi> by triall of your plumbe rule: then take a boord made preciſe ſquare, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſide ſomewhat longer than the ſemidiameter of the circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> and ſet one corner thereof in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>A,</hi> ſo that one of the ſides containing it, may agrée iuſt with the Stéele or wier, and the other with the circles plaine: then looking along the vpper edge, or through two ſights ſet vpon the edge, and continually lifting it vp without ſwaruing, till the ſide that lay vpon the flat of the circle agrée with the Stéele: the line of your ſight, or the line drawne from the center (for in reſpect of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens mightie diſtance, the difference betwéene them is not ſenſible) ſhall, howſoeuer the ſquare be placed, deſcribe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13856:7"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                  </figure> an Azimute. And if ſtaying the edge of the ſquare at one height, the corner be continually kept in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> center without ſlipping, by turning it round about the Stéele, you ſhall deſcribe an Almicantar, parallel to the Horizon. In this manner, carying the ſquare about, &amp; lifting it vp &amp; downe, till you ſee the Pole ſtarre, or if you can aime at it, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſpoken of immoueable poynt, ſtaying it faſt in that ſituation, either of the edges without ſenſible error may bee taken for the Axis of the world, which extended fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on both the Poles, that which is ſeene being the Arc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Pole, and the Antarctick that which is vnder the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon. In lifting it vp and downe, you ſhall in the heauen poynt out the Meridian circle, and bringing it iuſt to the flat of the circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> the edge will there ſhew the right line <hi>B D,</hi> which is the Meridian line. The line <hi>C E,</hi> in <hi>A</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13856:7"/>croſſing the line <hi>B D,</hi> is the line of right Eaſt, and right Weſt: the Azimute ſtanding vpon <hi>C E,</hi> is the Vertical circle, or the circle of the Eaſt: the Azimute ſtanding vpon <hi>G F,</hi> is ſometime ſaid to be of ſo many degrees, as are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene <hi>B</hi> the North poynt of the Horizon, and <hi>G,</hi> where the Azimute ſtanding vpon <hi>G F</hi> cutteth the Horizon, <hi>vz.</hi> the circumference <hi>B G,</hi> denominateth the Azimute ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon <hi>G F,</hi> and ſometime that circumference <hi>G E,</hi> which containeth the number of the degrées betweéene the ſame poynt, and the line of Eaſt and Weſt <hi>E C,</hi> which bée the very poles of the Meridian. Working by the Pole ſtarre, theſe things will ſomewhat varie from exactnes, which ſome helpe by awayting the time, when the ſtarre next the whéeles of Charles wayne, commonly called the filler or hill horſe, is directly ouer or vnder the Pole ſtar, ſo that the ſquare, being lifted vp and downe cloſe by the Stéele, paſſeth by them both. But howſoeuer, this may ſuffice for ſome conceit of theſe termes, hereafter ſhall be taught other moſt preciſe waies, to diſcribe and take them moſt exactly. To returne againe therefore to our princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall purpoſe, in beholding of the Starres, how they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually riſing in the Eaſt ſide of the Horizon, aſcend vnto the Meridian, and ſo from thence deſcend vnto the Weſt ſide, you ſhall obſerue, that alwaies they kéepe their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Pole ſtarre, or the true pole vnchaunged: as if you mark the two hinder whéeles of Charles waine, you ſhall finde, howſoeuer they be ſituated in the heauen, that their diſtance from the Pole ſtarre is alwaies one, and the ſame not néerer or further of at one time then an other, and therefore euery ſtarre or poynt, by ſuch motion in a Globe or Sphere, his ſuperficies deſcribeth the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of a circle: ſo that the whole heauens muſt ſeeme to turne vpon the poles, and make a circular motion or reuolution. This motion in diuers reſpects hath diuers names, called ſometime the Diurnall motion, ſometime the motion of the firſt moueable heauen, ſometime <hi>Notus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13856:8"/>captus.</hi> Againe, euery Starre or peynt by this conuerſion deſcribing a circle, if you take ſome ſtarre, or poynt, which lieth betwéene the poles iuſt <hi>90.</hi> degrées from either of them, that will deſcribe a circle, paſſing by the poynts of Eaſt and Weſt, which for ſome reaſons hereafter to bee expreſſed, is called the Equinoctiall. The other poynts or ſtarres deſcribe circles parallel to the Equinoctiall circle, which be called circles of declination, becauſe, if from the poles of the world, by any point taken in any of the paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels, a greateſt circle be drawne to the Equinoctiall, that portion of it, which lieth betwéene the Equinoctiall and the Parallel, is called the declination of the poynt ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. Some of theſe Parallels towards the North, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by reuolution of the poynts or ſtarres, that neuer ſet, are whole aboue the Horizon, and one of them, which ſome name the Arctick circle, toucheth it onely: about the Antarcticke pole there be ſome wholy vnder the Horizon, and one, which ſome call the Antarcticke circle, only tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth it in the South poynt: other betwéene theſe two touching Parallels, which ariſe and ſet or goe downe, cut the Horizon, whoſe portion lying betwéene that poynt and the true Eaſt or Weſt, is called the Amplitude or Latitude of the riſing, or the ſetting of the poynt deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Parallel. Theſe things hitherto rehearſed, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers may euery where and in all countries obſerue: and beſides, in their iournies Southward or Northward, they ſhall ſee ſometimes more, and ſometimes fewer ſtars neuer to goe downe: more in going Northward, fewer in going Southward, yet alwaies without alteration kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping one and the ſame diſtance one from another. Mary the Pole ſtarre or the true pole, proportionablie to the length of the way trauelled, altereth his diſtance from the Horizon, and the Zenith appearing, the further you goe Northward, the higher, &amp; the further you go Southward, the lower, and ſo accordingly that portion of the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, betwéene the Equinoctiall and the Zenith, which is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13856:8"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                  </figure> called the Latitude of the countrie, being alwaies equall to that which is betwéene the Horizon and the Pole, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his height, or eleuation, is of neceſſitie greater or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer: ſo that your ſituation is apparantly chaunged in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the heauen, but yet ſtil you kéepe the ſame diſtance from it, wherby you may eaſily inferre the figure or ſhape of the Earth to bee like and anſwerable to the celeſtiall Sphere: and that how vaſt and huge ſoeuer it be in it ſelf, yet in compariſon of the large compaſſe of the heauen, it is iuſtly counted for no more but a ſmall poynt, or pricke: for it neuer hindreth you from ſeeing the preciſe halfe of the celeſtiall Sphere, which, were the bignes thereof any thing of accompt, it would of neceſſitie doe. For better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of theſe matters, imagine the circle <hi>B C D E,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13856:9"/>deſcribed on the center <hi>A,</hi> to repreſent the Meridian, and vpon the line <hi>E C,</hi> a ſemicircle erected perpendicularly to repreſent the Horizon, whoſe Pole, or the Zenith, the poynt <hi>B</hi> is, and let <hi>H</hi> be the North pole. From <hi>H</hi> to <hi>A</hi> the place of your ſtanding (being the center of the Horizon and the whole Sphere, and ſo conſequently of al the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt circles in the ſame Sphere deſcribed) from the pole <hi>H</hi> to the center <hi>A</hi> draw a right line, and extend it vnto <hi>I:</hi> the line <hi>H I</hi> is the Axis of the world: the poles be <hi>H</hi> the North, and <hi>I</hi> the South, or Antarcticke pole. Let the poynt <hi>G,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Meridian, be iuſt <hi>90.</hi> degrees from either pole, ſo that the circumferences <hi>G H, G I,</hi> be iuſt quadrants: by the reuolution of the Sphere vpon the poles <hi>H I,</hi> which is the Diurnall motion, the line <hi>G A</hi> ſhall deſcribe a circle paſſing by the center of the Sphere, and perpendicular to the Meridian: therefore it muſt paſſe by the poles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of which be in the Horizon, the points of Eaſt and Weſt, as the circle ſet plumbe vpon the Diameter <hi>F G</hi> will doe. Other poynts, as <hi>S, N, V,</hi> deſcribes circles parallel to that ſtanding vpon <hi>G F,</hi> of which that which ſtandeth vpon <hi>C S,</hi> doth onely touch the Horizon, and is wholy aboue it: the other beyond it to the pole-ward, as <hi>V, W,</hi> be wholy aboue it, and come not néere. So likewiſe <hi>E, T,</hi> is alwayes vnder the Horizon, and only toucheth it: the other beyond it towards <hi>I,</hi> are vnder it, and neuer come néere it. Now if in going Northward the pole <hi>H</hi> grow higher, the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall muſt go further from the Zenith: for ſeeing <hi>B C</hi> and <hi>G H</hi> be equall, that is the iuſt quarters of the ſame circle, if you take away the circumference <hi>B H</hi> common to them both, the reſidue <hi>G B,</hi> the diſtance of the Equinoctial from the Meridian, which is the Latitude of the countrie, whoſe Zenith is <hi>B,</hi> is equall to <hi>H C,</hi> the height of the pole aboue the Horizon, or the eleuation of the pole, and as the pole riſeth higher, ſo is the circle <hi>S</hi> Cremoued from the Horizon further and further: whereby you ſee, that by that meanes more ſtarres neuer ſet. The circumferences
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13856:9"/>of the Meridian <hi>G N, G S, G V,</hi> are called the declinations of the points <hi>N, S, V,</hi> taken in the parallels <hi>N Z, S C, V W,</hi> and the portion of the Horizon betwéene the point of true Eaſt, and the poynt, where the parallel ſtanding vpon <hi>N Z,</hi> cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth the Horizon, is the amplitude or latitude of riſing of the poynt <hi>L,</hi> or any other taken in the parallel, ſtanding vpon the Diameter <hi>N Z.</hi> Theſe things being well conceiued, let vs conſider againe, that as apparantly as any ſtarre, the Sunne making his reuolution, ariſeth on the Eaſt ſide of the Horizon, and mounting vp vnto the Meridian, at which time it is high noone, deſcendeth againe vnto the Weſt ſide, which time of his continuance aboue the Horizon is called the artificiall day, then being hid from our ſight, the night beginneth, which continueth till the Sunne, paſſing by that part of the Meridian, which is vnder the Earth, when it is midnight with vs, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againe vnto the Eaſt ſide, making vp the naturall day, which is the ſpace of time from the Sunne riſing to the Sunne riſing againe, and may bee indifferently recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from Sunne ſet to Sunne ſet, as the Iewes doe, or from midnight to midnight, which is our common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt. The obſcure light before the Sunnes riſing, is called the dawning and breake of the day: after his ſetting is called the twilight, <hi>Crepuſculum</hi> in Latin is a common name to both times. Although in the Sunnes daily reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution we obſerue all this, yet is it not without much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie and chaunge: his riſing and ſetting is not alwayes in one place of the Horizon, nor his height in the Meridian alwayes the ſame at noone. In the middeſt of winter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>12.</hi> of our December, when the daies be ſhorteſt, and the nights longeſt, it riſeth &amp; ſetteth moſt Southerly, and is loweſt in the Meridian at noone: towards the Spring, as the dayes waxe longer and longer, in riſing and ſetting it continually groweth from the South, and mounteth higher and higher in the Meridian, till about the <hi>11.</hi> of our March, making the day and night equall, it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13856:10"/>riſeth and ſetteth iuſt Eaſt and Weſt, comming at noone to the common ſection of the Equinoctiall and the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian: then, as Summer commeth on, the dayes encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, it riſeth and ſetteth more Northerly, mounting ſtill higher and higher in the Meridian at noone, till in the middeſt of Summer, the dayes being at the longeſt, about the <hi>12.</hi> of our Iune, it be at the higheſt in the Meridian at noone, and riſeth and ſetteth furtheſt North: then, as the dayes ſhorten, it returneth backe againe, growing conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually lower at noone, and riſing and ſetting leſſe Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, till the dayes and nights become equall againe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>13.</hi> of our September, when it riſeth and ſetteth preciſely Eaſt and Weſt againe, and at noone will be in the common ſection of the Equinoctiall and the Meridian. From that poynt it groweth lower and lower at noone, riſing &amp; ſetting more and more Southerly, as the nights encreaſe, till about the <hi>12.</hi> of our December the dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the ſhorteſt, it becommeth loweſt againe at noone, and in riſing and ſetting moſt Southerly, as it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Of this returning from the higheſt in Summer, and the loweſt in winter, the two Parallels, which it then deſcribeth by the Diurnall reuolution, bee called Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pickes, and the Equinoctiall was ſo named, becauſe in March and September the Sunne comming to it, the day is made equall to the night. By theſe varieties it was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily gathered, that the Sunne made a peculiar courſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his Diurnall reuolution, in a greateſt circle touching the two Tropicks, and declining from the Equinoctiall, which it diuideth (as all greateſt circles doe one another) into two equall parts, or ſemicircles. This declining circle, becauſe when the Sunne and Moone either méete or be oppoſite in it, there happeneth an Eclipſe, is called the Eclipticke, and ſometime the Zodiacke: but the Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacke properly is a ſuperficies like a fillet or a girdle, laid vpon this circles circumference, comprehending on either ſide of it ſixe, or (as ſome ſay) eight degrées. The poles of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13856:10"/>this circle, which decline from the poles of the world, as the circle it ſelfe declineth from the Equinoctiall, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth by the Diurnall reuolution two Parallels, which ſome, in ſtead of them afore deſcribed, take for the Arctick and Antarcticke circles. That ſection of the Equinoctial and the Eclipticke, which the Sunne commeth to in the Spring time, is called the Vernall ſection: that which is oppoſite to it, by which the Sunne paſſeth in the end of Harueſt, is the Autumnall ſection: the poynts which touch the Tropickes, bee commonly called Solſtitiall poynts. The greateſt circle, paſſing by the Equinoctiall ſections and the poles of the world, is the Equinoctiall Colure: that which paſſeth by the poles of the world and the Solſtitiall poynts, is called the Solſtitiall, or Tropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Colure, the portion thereof lying betwéene the two Tropickes, is the diſtance of the Tropickes, whoſe halfe is the Sunnes greateſt declination, otherwiſe called the Obliquitie of the Zodiacke, which by obſeruation made with large inſtruments, is in this our age found by great Artes-men to be <hi>23.</hi> degrées and <hi>30.</hi> minutes, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it ſhall be ſufficient to accept of, and commit to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, without taking or trying it by any ſmall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: though ſome writers of the vſe of the Aſtrolabe haue made that one of their ſpeciall concluſions. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall and the Eclipticke, are circles of chiefe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt: the firſt being the rule and meaſure of the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or the motion of <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> otherwiſe called the Diurnall reuolution: and the other as it were the Standard, whereby all ſecondarie motions are exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: therefore the degrées of theſe circles haue peculiar names, called in the Equinoctiall <hi>Tempora,</hi> times, becauſe they be the firſt meaſures of time, euery <hi>15.</hi> degrées aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding making an houre, and ſo the whole reuolution of <hi>360.</hi> which is performed euery naturall day, make <hi>24.</hi> houres. Aſtronomers begin to accompt the parts or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées, as well in the Equinoctiall, as in the Eclipticke,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13856:11"/>from that poynt common to them both, which is called the Vernall ſection: and though in the Equinoctiall there be no chaunge of names, yet in the Eclipticke or Zodiacke euery thirtie degrées is called a ſigne, and hath a peculiar name. The firſt <hi>30.</hi> immedtatly following the Vernall ſection, is called <hi>Aries:</hi> the next <hi>30. Taurus,</hi> the third <hi>30. Gemini,</hi> the fourth <hi>30.</hi> (whoſe firſt point begin a new qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, and toucheth the Summer Tropicke) is termed <hi>Cancer:</hi> the fift <hi>30. Leo,</hi> the ſixt <hi>Virgo.</hi> Theſe ſixe Signes make vp the ſemicircle of the Zodiacke, which leaneth or declineth from the Equinoctiall toward the North pole. The firſt <hi>30.</hi> after this ſemicircle, beginning at the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumnall ſection, make the ſeuenth ſigne, named <hi>Libra:</hi> the next or eight <hi>30.</hi> is the ſigne <hi>Scorpio:</hi> the ninth <hi>30.</hi> is <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gittarius:</hi> the tenth <hi>30.</hi> (beginning a new quadrant with the firſt poynt, which toucheth the winter Tropicke) is <hi>Capricornus:</hi> the eleuenth <hi>30.</hi> is <hi>Aquarius,</hi> and the twelfth <hi>30.</hi> is <hi>Piſces.</hi> There be characters vſed to expreſſe euery Signe with, which are found in euery Almanacke. The Sunne paſſeth in the Ecliptick from poynt to poynt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his continuall reuolution in it, without ſwaruing to the one ſide or the other: other Starres for the moſt part decline from it, but yet haue their places determined by Longitude and Latitude in reſpect thereof thus: By any poynt or Starre, a greateſt circle being drawne from the pole of the Ecliptick to his circumference, the ſection there made, or the portion of the Ecliptick betwéene that ſection and the Vernall ſection, is the Longitude of the poynt, or Starre, by which the greateſt circle is drawne: his Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is that portion of the ſame greateſt circle lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Starre and the Eclipticke. The Sunne being in any poynt of the Eclipticke, and the poynt it ſelfe, with all other Starres, whereſoeuer placed beſides, are in like manner compared to the Equinoctiall, and in reſpect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, not onely their declination, which hath béen touched before, but alſo their right Aſcenſion is conſidered. A
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13856:11"/>greateſt circle being drawne from the Poles of the world to the Equinoctiall, by any poynt or Starre, his right Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion is that portion of the Equinoctiall, taken betwéen that poynt where the greateſt circle cutteth, and the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſection. The declination is the portion of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt circle ſo drawne, which lieth betwéene the Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and the Starre, which (as before was noted) is alſo determined by a Parallel to the Equinoctiall, paſſing by the Starre. The right Aſcenſion is ſo called, becauſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Equinoctiall, that is, in a Situation where the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall paſſeth by the Zenith, and the Horizon by the Poles of the world, the Horizon (by which once in <hi>24.</hi> houres euery poynt aſcendeth) doth the office of any grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt circle ſo drawne, as is appoynted, and agréeth with it moſt exactly. This Situation is called <hi>Sphaera recta,</hi> the right Sphere; and the Horizon in that Situation, <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon rectus,</hi> the right Horizon: but when the Equinoctiall declineth from the Zenith, and the Poles bée one aboue, the other beneath the Horizon, that Situation is called the Oblique, or Declining Sphere; and the Horizon, the Oblique Horizon, which neuer agréeth with the foreſayd greateſt circle, drawne by the Poles of the world: and therefore with the Starre there is another poynt of the Equinoctiall in the Horizon, betwéene which and the Vernall ſection is contained that portion of the Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, that is called the Starres Oblique Aſcenſion, and the portion of the Equinoctiall betwéene the ends of the right and Oblique Aſcenſion, is called the Difference Aſcenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. But for helping the conceit of theſe things, I will vſe a linearie example, taking the former figure, where <hi>E C</hi> is the Meridian line, and the Diameter on which the Horizon ſtandeth, now in the middeſt of winter the Sun being loweſt in the Meridian, in the point <hi>K,</hi> by the Diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reuolution, deſcribeth a Parallel ſtanding vpon the Diameter <hi>K M,</hi> which cutteth the Horizon from the Eaſt towards the South: it continually groweth higher and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13856:12"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                  </figure> higher in the Meridian pan, &amp; riſeth in the Horizon néerer and néerer the Eaſt, till about the <hi>11.</hi> of March at noone it commeth to <hi>G,</hi> the ſection of the Equinoctiall and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian, and then by the Diurnall reuolution deſcribeth a circle iuſt anſwering the Equinoctiall, which paſſing by the poynts of Eaſt and Weſt in the Horizon, ſtandeth vpon the Diameter <hi>G F:</hi> from thence, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Summer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on, it aſcendeth in the Meridian, and riſeth more Northerly vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Horizon, til about the <hi>12.</hi> of our Iune, being at the higheſt in <hi>N,</hi> it deſcribeth a Parallel ſtanding vpon the Diameter <hi>N Z,</hi> in which it riſeth vpon the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon furtheſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Eaſt to the Northward: from thence it deſcendeth againe by <hi>G,</hi> to <hi>K,</hi> and paſſeth in the Horizon by the true Eaſt to the furtheſt Southward, then it aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13856:12"/>againe till it come to <hi>N,</hi> continually returning from the higheſt to the loweſt, &amp; from the loweſt to the higheſt: whereof the two Parallels ſtanding vpon the Diameters <hi>K M, L N,</hi> be called Tropickes. By theſe changes it was eaſily gathered, that the Sunne (beſides the Diurnall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution) made another proper to it ſelfe in a circle ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon the Diameter <hi>K L,</hi> drawne from Tropicke to Tropick by <hi>A</hi> the center of the Sphere: by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, this circle, called the Eclipticke, and the Equinoctiall, diuide the one the other into two ſemicircles. The Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke is ſometimes called the Zodiacke, though properly the Zodiacke be a ſuperficies lying on either ſide of it, as you ſée the ſuperficies <hi>O P Q R,</hi> parted by the line <hi>Z K.</hi> The common Diameter of the Equinoctiall and the Ecliptick ſtanding in <hi>A,</hi> perpendicular to the plaine of the circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> the poynts <hi>K</hi> and <hi>L</hi> being the Solſtitiall poynts, the circle <hi>B C D E</hi> is the Solſtitiall Colure. The circle ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon <hi>I H,</hi> and paſſing by the perpendicular Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the Equinoctial ſection, is the Equinoctiall Colure: the circumference <hi>K N</hi> is the diſtance of the Tropicke, the one halfe thereof <hi>G K,</hi> or <hi>G N,</hi> is the obliquitie of the Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diacke, or the Suns greateſt declination, for it groweth leſſe &amp; leſſe as it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth néerer the Equinoctiall ſection: where it hath no declination at al, it neuer declineth from the Eclipticke or circle ſtanding vpon <hi>K Z,</hi> but make his motion in it, his place is named of the poynt wherein it is. Other Starres or poynts without the Eclipticke (as for example, <hi>S</hi>) haue their place determined by a greateſt circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> drawne from <hi>X,</hi> the Pole of the Zodiacke, by <hi>S</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>K,</hi> a poynt in the Ecliptick circumference, the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ecliptick betwéene the Vernall ſection and <hi>K,</hi> or the poynt <hi>K</hi> is the Longitude of <hi>S,</hi> and the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>S K,</hi> is his Latitude. In like manner, if by any ſtarre or poynt <hi>Y,</hi> and the Poles of the worlde <hi>H I,</hi> there bee drawne a greateſt circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> cutting the Equinoctiall in <hi>G,</hi> the portion of the Equinoctiall betwéene the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13856:13"/>ſection and <hi>G,</hi> is the right Aſcenſion of <hi>Y,</hi> and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference <hi>G Y</hi> is his declination. Now if <hi>G,</hi> the ſection of the Meridian and the Equinoctiall, be the Zenith of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place, the Horizon muſt ſtand on <hi>I H,</hi> and paſſe by the Poles of the world, which ſituation is called the right Sphere, and the Horizon the right Horizon, wherein, by the Diurnall reuolution twice in <hi>24.</hi> houres, the circle <hi>B C D E</hi> muſt ioyne cloſe with it. But if <hi>G,</hi> the ſection of the Equinoctiall and the Meridian, decline from <hi>B</hi> the Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith, which ſituation is called the Oblique Sphere, and the Horizon then ſtanding on <hi>E C,</hi> being an Oblique Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, by the Diurnall motion made vpon the Poles <hi>H I,</hi> the circle <hi>B C D E</hi> can neuer agréene or match euenly with the Horizon: therefore of force ſome other poynt of the Equinoctiall, and not <hi>G,</hi> muſt be in the Horizon with <hi>Y:</hi> the circumference of the Equinoctiall betwéene that point in the Horizon, and the Vernall ſection, is the Oblique Aſcenſion of <hi>Y:</hi> but the portion that lieth betwéene that poynt and <hi>G,</hi> is the difference Aſcenſionall. That poynt of the Zodiacke, where it is cut off the Meridian, is called <hi>Medium coeli,</hi> mid heauen; <hi>Culmen</hi> and <hi>cor coeli</hi> aboue the Horizon, &amp; <hi>Imum coeli</hi> vnder the Horizon, the leſſer angle, made by that ſection, is called the Meridian angle. The poynt of the Eclipticke, that is in the Eaſt ſide of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, is called the Aſcendent, and the Horoſcope, the ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there make the angles, of which the leſſer is called the Horizontall angle: the quantitie thereof is equall to the <hi>Nonageſimus Gradus</hi> of the Eclipticke, which is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly giuen to that poynt of it, which is iuſt <hi>90.</hi> degrées from the Aſcendent. There be moreouer other greateſt circles to be conſidered, which are called circles of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or circles of Station, ſixe of them diuiding the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in twelue portions, which are called houſes or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, though many times thoſe names be reſtrained on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuch parts of the Zodiack, as be intercepted by thoſe circles. Though the Horizon be alwaies taken for one,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13856:13"/>and the beginning of the firſt houſe: yet are the reſt by diuers diuerſly drawne. Some will haue them all to haue the Meridian line for their common Diameter, and yet agréeing in this make difference in placing them. <hi>Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Gazulus</hi> diuide the Verticall circle into twelue equall parts, and by euery two oppoſite ſections draw a circle of poſition. <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> diuideth the Equinoctial into twelue equall parts, and will haue euery circle of poſition paſſe by two of thoſe oppoſite ſections: both theſe waies kéepe the Horizon and the Meridian for circles of poſition. Other diuide the Zodiacke into twelue equall parts, beginning at the Aſcendent, and two of thoſe oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite ſections draw from the poles of the Zodiacke their circles of poſition: theſe kéepe the ſame Aſcendent that the former doe, but muſt differ many times in the tenth houſe, or the <hi>Cardo medij coeli,</hi> though <hi>Gemma</hi> writeth that all agrée about the foruer <hi>Cardines,</hi> that is the Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope, ſeuenth houſe <hi>Culmen,</hi> and <hi>Imum coeli:</hi> for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue alwaies the Meridian &amp; the Horizon for circles of poſition. Other draw theſe circles from the poles of the world, and that diuerſly: but the thrée former wayes are in greateſt eſtimation. A circle of poſition differeth from an angle of poſition, which (after <hi>Prolomey</hi>) is an angle at the Zenith, ſubtended of that portion of the Horizon, which lieth betwéene the Meridian and the Azimute, paſſing by the Zenith of the other place, vnto which the poſition belongeth. <hi>Gemma Friſius</hi> maketh it a right lined angle in the center of the Horizon, ſubtended of the ſame circumference: by it Topographicall deſcriptions are made, wherein ſometimes the diſtance of two places is meaſured by a right line lying betwéene them, but in a Sphericall ſuperficies by the portion of a greateſt circle, becauſe that is the ſhorteſt that can bee drawne in it. Theſe things may be eaſily conceiued without linearie explication, if the former matters bee well vnderſtood: therefore as it were beſides the principall purpoſe, ſetting
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13856:14"/>downe how by ſupputation you may readily geſſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what néere the Suns place, being a thing for many pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to be had in a readines, I will end this firſt ſection: the thing is taken out of <hi>Clauius,</hi> but fitted to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or the Iulian yeere.</p>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Parergon primum.</hi> What moneth, and what day of it, the Sunne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth euery ſigne of the Zodiacke.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt tell the moneths vpon your fingers, ſeeking In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarie on your thumbe, Februarie on your forefinger, and ſo the other in order, till you come to your moneth, which marke on which finger it falleth: in like manner tell the Signes, beginning with <hi>Aquarius</hi> on your thumb, <hi>Piſces</hi> on your forefinger, and ſo the reſt in order, till you come to the finger, on which your moneth fell: the Signe which falleth on that finger, the Sunne entreth that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. Then learning theſe two verſes by heart:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Inclyta Laus Iuſtis Impenditur, Haereſis Horret</l>
                     <l>Garrula, Grex Gratus Fauſtos Gratatur Honores.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>In like manner ſet <hi>Inclyta</hi> on your thumbe, and word by word in order, till you come to the finger, on which your moneth fell: then telling from <hi>A</hi> in the croſſe row, till you come to the firſt letter of your word, take that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and ſubtract it from <hi>20.</hi> the reſidue is the day of the moneth, when the Sunne entreth the Signe. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: I would know what Signe the Sunne entreth in October, and what day it entreth, telling from Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vpon my fingers the meneths in order: at the ſecond going ouer I finde October on my little finger: then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Signes, and telling from <hi>Aquarius,</hi> at the ſecond going ouer my fingers, <hi>Scorpio</hi> falleth on my little fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo I ſay that the Sunne entreth <hi>Scorpio</hi> in October: then taking the verſes, and ſetting the words one by one
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13856:14"/>in like manner on my fingers, I finde in the ſecond going ouer, <hi>Fauſtos</hi> on my little finger: now telling in the croſſe row the letters from <hi>A</hi> to <hi>F,</hi> I finde ſixe: this ſixe I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from <hi>20.</hi> ſo reſt <hi>14.</hi> which the day of October the Sunne entreth <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Parergon ſecundum.</hi> To know the Sunnes place in the Zodiacke vpon any day giuen.</head>
                  <p>FInde the Signe anſwering your moneth, and the word likewiſe, then to the day of the moneth put ten, and the number the firſt letter ſheweth in the croſſe row: if this be leſſe then <hi>30.</hi> the number is the degrée of the Signe next before that, which the Sunne entreth in your moneth; if more, caſt away <hi>30.</hi> and the reſidue is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée of the Signe entred in your moneth. Example, I would know where the Sunne is the <hi>9.</hi> of October, I finde in October he entreth <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and the word for it to be <hi>Fauſtos,</hi> whoſe firſt letter <hi>F</hi> is the ſixt in the croſſe row, I take ten and <hi>6. vz. 16.</hi> which I put to, <hi>9.</hi> there is made <hi>25.</hi> therefore I ſay the Sun is in the <hi>25.</hi> degree of the Signe before <hi>Scorpio,</hi> which is <hi>Libra.</hi> If I would know for the <hi>18.</hi> day, putting <hi>16.</hi> to <hi>18.</hi> there would amount <hi>34.</hi> from which abating <hi>30.</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> remaining ſheweth me, that the Sunne is in the <hi>4.</hi> degrée of the Signe belonging to October, which is <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Parergon tertium.</hi> The place of the Sunne being giuen, to finde the day of the moneth.</head>
                  <p>TAke the day and moneth the Sun entreth the Signe giuen, the number of the degrées giuen put to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13856:15"/>day, wherein the Sunne entreth the Signe, that product being leſſe than the dayes in your moneth, ſhew the day: but being more, caſt away the dayes of your moneth, the reſidue is the day of the moneth following. Example, I finde the Sunne in the <hi>4.</hi> degrée of <hi>Scorpio.</hi> I would know what day of the moneth it is; I finde that the Sunne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth <hi>Scorpio</hi> the <hi>14.</hi> of October, I put <hi>4.</hi> to <hi>14.</hi> there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth <hi>18.</hi> ſo I ſay it is the <hi>18.</hi> day of October. Againe, let it be in the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>Libra,</hi> I finde that the Sunne entreth <hi>Libra 13. Septembris:</hi> I put <hi>13.</hi> to <hi>25.</hi> there amounteth <hi>38.</hi> from which I take <hi>30.</hi> the dayes of September, and there remaineth <hi>8.</hi> the day of October. Theſe are but geſſes, as you may ſee much after the way commonly taught by the backe of the Aſtrolabe. Let him that deſireth exactnes, ſeeke the Sunnes place in ſome Ephemerides, or in the Regiment of the Sunne, publiſhed by <hi>E. W.</hi> painfully calculated vpon his owne diligent and exact ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations.</p>
                  <trailer>The end of the firſt Section.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13856:15"/>
               <head>THE SECOND SEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE NEW HANDLING THE PLANISPHERE; SHEWING HOW THE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of the Aſtrolabe may readily and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for any Countrie be performed onely with Ruler and Compaſſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough for working the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions following any circle diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or to tranſferre out of any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided quadrant, the giuen circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences would be ſufficient: yet for the eaſier diſpatch, I would a plate of Latten to be prouided, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the figure which you ſée on the other ſide. There, vpon one center <hi>A,</hi> be ſixe circles deſcribed one within another, of which the two outtermoſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth the narroweſt ſpace, which muſt be diuided into <hi>360.</hi> equall parts or degrées, as the common manner is. At euery <hi>30.</hi> degrées, in the ſpace contained vnder the ſecond and third circles, make diuiſious, and beginning at <hi>E</hi> write <hi>Ari,</hi> or <hi>Aries:</hi> at the next, <hi>Tau,</hi> or <hi>Taurus,</hi> and ſo for the reſt of the <hi>12.</hi> Signes: this circle ſhall be called the Zodiacke. The third ſpace, contained vnder the third and fourth circle, muſt bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13856:16"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                  </figure> at euery <hi>15.</hi> degrées: beginning at <hi>B</hi> you muſt ſet downe <hi>12.</hi> at the next diuiſion toward <hi>C</hi> ſet downe <hi>1.</hi> at the next <hi>2.</hi> and at euery diuiſion the numbers in order, till comming to <hi>D,</hi> you are to ſet downe <hi>12.</hi> againe: and ſo in the other ſemicircle <hi>DEB,</hi> ſet <hi>1.</hi> at the diuiſion next <hi>D,</hi> at
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13856:16"/>the ſecond <hi>2.</hi> till comming to the next before <hi>B,</hi> you are to ſet downe <hi>11:</hi> this fourth circle ſhall be called the houre circle. The fourth ſpace, contained vnder the fourth and fift circle, muſt be diuided at euery <hi>10.</hi> degrées: at the firſt diuiſion from <hi>E</hi> towards <hi>B</hi> ſet <hi>10.</hi> at the ſecond <hi>20.</hi> and ſo encreaſing continually at euery diuiſion by <hi>10.</hi> till you come againe to <hi>E,</hi> where you are to ſet downe <hi>360.</hi> this circle ſhall be named the Equinoctiall. The ſpace contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder this and the ſixt, or innermoſt circle, muſt from <hi>E</hi> by <hi>D</hi> vnto <hi>C,</hi> haue diuiſions at euery <hi>20.</hi> degrées, and at euery diuiſion a number ſet encreaſing by <hi>10.</hi> til you come to <hi>90:</hi> in the quarters <hi>B C, B E,</hi> you muſt make diuiſions at euery <hi>10.</hi> degrees: at the firſt, from <hi>B</hi> towards <hi>E,</hi> ſet <hi>10,</hi> and likewiſe at the next vnto <hi>C</hi> towards <hi>B,</hi> at the next <hi>20.</hi> and ſo in order, till comming to <hi>E</hi> and <hi>B,</hi> you are there to ſet <hi>90:</hi> this inner circle ſhall be called the limbe. If you will ſet two ſights on the outter edge, ſo that the line, drawne from lope to lope, be parallel to the line ſubten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the arch <hi>B C,</hi> and hang a plummet from <hi>B,</hi> you may by your plate begin.</p>
               <div n="1" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt Concluſion.</hi> To take the height of the Sunne, or any Starre, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Horizon.</head>
                  <p>TVrning your plate towards the Sunne, lift it vp and downe, till his beames ſhine through both the lopes of your ſights, or (if it be a Starre) till you ſee it through them: the thréed ſheweth in the ſemicircle <hi>E D C,</hi> how many degrées the Sunne or Starre is aboue the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13856:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond Concluſion.</hi> To finde the diſtance of the Sunnes or any Starres Azimute, from any determinate poynt in the Horizon.</head>
                  <p>LEt your plate be fixed leuell with the Horizon, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect <hi>E</hi> to any poynt: then a ruler being turned and lift vp by a ſtéele or wier, ſtanding plumbe vpright from the center <hi>A,</hi> till you ſee the ſtarre, by the edge of it, or rather through two ſights ſet vpon the edge, or if it be the Sun, till his beames paſſe through the lopes, then without ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the end next your eye bring it cloſe to the center, the edge ſheweth in the Equinoctiall the diſtance of the Azi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute from the poynt reſpected by <hi>E.</hi> The Azimute is ſayd ſimply without adition to bee giuen, when his diſtance from the Meridians North end is giuen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third Concluſion.</hi> From a point giuen in the circumference of a circle, at any ſide aſſigned, to applie or ſubtend a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or a right line not greater than the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter.</head>
                  <p>LEt the poynt giuen be <hi>C,</hi> from which vpon the ſide towards <hi>D,</hi> I am to applie a line equall to <hi>A Q,</hi> draw the Diameter <hi>C A E:</hi> now if the line <hi>A Q</hi> be equall to the Diameter, I haue done that which is required: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſſe, I take the diſtance <hi>A Q</hi> with my Compaſſe, and ſetting one foote in <hi>C,</hi> with the other I marke <hi>Q</hi> in the limbe, and ſo vnder the circumference <hi>C Q,</hi> I haue ſubten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a diſtance equall to <hi>A Q,</hi> which was required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13856:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourth Concluſion.</hi> From a point giuen in any circles circumference, to take at any ſide aſſigned, an arch equall to any arch giuen in the ſame, or any equall circle.</head>
                  <p>FRom the poynt giuen <hi>C,</hi> draw the Diameter <hi>C A E:</hi> now if the arch giuen be a ſemicircle, the circumfere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <hi>C D E,</hi> taken at the ſide aſſigned <hi>D,</hi> is the arch deſired: but if it be leſſer, as <hi>F G,</hi> I take the diſtance <hi>F G,</hi> and ſetting one foote of the Compaſſe in <hi>C,</hi> with the other towards <hi>D,</hi> I marke <hi>3</hi> in the limbe, the circumference <hi>3 C</hi> is that, which is deſired: but if it be greater than a ſemicircle, as <hi>6 G,</hi> I take in like manner with my Compaſſe the diſtance <hi>6 G,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>C,</hi> on the other ſide towards <hi>B,</hi> not on that which was aſſigned towards <hi>D,</hi> I marke in the limbe with the other foote <hi>L,</hi> the circumference <hi>C D L</hi> is that, which is required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fift Concluſion.</hi> The heights or Almicanters, together with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betweene the Azimutes of any two Stars giuen, or taken by obſeruation, to finde the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one from another.</head>
                  <p>VPon the center <hi>A</hi> deſcribe a circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> and let the Diameters <hi>B D, C E,</hi> bee perpendiculars one to another. This conſtruction ſhall bee alwaies aſſumed herafter without further expreſſing: from <hi>E</hi> to <hi>H</hi> reckon the diſtance of the Azimutes, and draw the line <hi>A H:</hi> then taking the circumference <hi>E F,</hi> equall to the greateſt alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and making <hi>E G</hi> equall to it, vpon <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>N:</hi> againe, taking <hi>H I</hi> equall to the other altitude, make <hi>H K</hi> equall to it, a ruler layd on I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13856:18"/>and <hi>K,</hi> will cut <hi>A H</hi> in <hi>P,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>N P,</hi> and ſetting one foote of the Compaſſe in <hi>A,</hi> with the other in <hi>A B</hi> mark <hi>Q:</hi> againe, taking the diſtance <hi>F N,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>A,</hi> take the line <hi>A S:</hi> againe make the line <hi>S T</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>P I,</hi> opening your Compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>T Q,</hi> ſetting one feote in <hi>C,</hi> with the other in the limbe mark <hi>4,</hi> the circumference <hi>C 4</hi> is the diſtance ſought. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction is generall, but in ſome caſes may be abridged: for if the Altitudes were equall, it ſhould ſuffice to applie the diſtance <hi>N P</hi> in the limbe without any more adoe: if both were in one Azimute betwéene the Horizon and the Zenith, as <hi>E F</hi> being the greater, and <hi>F L</hi> the leſſer, the diſtance ſhould be <hi>L E:</hi> but if the Zenith were betwéene the height, whereof <hi>E M</hi> were the one, laying a ruler on <hi>M</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> it would cut the limbes beyond <hi>A</hi> in <hi>6.</hi> then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>B,</hi> taking the other height <hi>6.1.</hi> the diſtance ſhall be <hi>E B. 1.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſixt Concluſion.</hi> In any Countrie vnknowne to finde the Diameter of the Parallel of the Sunne, or any vnknowne Starre.</head>
                  <p>THrée times in one day, or for any Starre in the night, take the height and diſtance of the Azimute from any certaine poynt, whereby you may haue the diſtance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Azimute from other, by the former concluſion: take the diſtance of the poynts obſerued one from another, which let bee <hi>C 6. 6 B</hi> and <hi>B K</hi> of thrée lines equall to the chords, of thoſe circumferences, make a triangle <hi>C B A,</hi> and about it deſcribe a circle <hi>A B C,</hi> whoſe Diameter <hi>A C</hi> is the Parallels Diameter.</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13856:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſeuenth Concluſion.</hi> The Diameter of the Sunnes, or any Starres parallel being giuen, to finde the declination.</head>
                  <p>FRom <hi>C</hi> on either ſide applie a diſtance equall to <hi>A C,</hi> as <hi>C 1. C 2.</hi> vpon <hi>1</hi> &amp; <hi>2</hi> a ruler layd, will cut <hi>A C</hi> in <hi>R:</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13856:19"/>vpon <hi>R,</hi> as a center at the diſtance <hi>A R,</hi> deſcribe a ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circle <hi>A B C</hi> (a ſemicircle thus deſcribed, hauing one angle in the center <hi>A,</hi> and his Diameter the Semidiameter of the limbe, as <hi>A C</hi> is, ſhall hereafter be called the Synicall arch of the limbe). Now from <hi>C</hi> towards <hi>D</hi> apply at <hi>12</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>A C,</hi> the Parallels Diameter giuen, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>C</hi> and <hi>2.</hi> laying a ruler it will cut the Semicircle <hi>A B C</hi> in <hi>D,</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>D,</hi> it will cut the limbe in <hi>5.5 C</hi> is the declination ſought for. In the Sun you may know, by the time of the yéere, whether it be Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly or Southerly, and to what quadrant it belongeth, ſauing when he is néere the Tropickes, or Equinoctiall ſections: for diſtinguiſhing thereof, make your obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions two, or thrée, or foure ſundrie dayes: then the Sun being about the Tropickes, comparing two obſeruations, if the declination encreaſe, the firſt obſeruation was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it came to the Tropicke: but if it decreaſe, the ſecond was after it came to the Tropicke, the Tropicke will ſhew North and South, from <hi>Aries by Cancer</hi> to <hi>Libra</hi> North, from thence by <hi>Capricornus</hi> to <hi>Aries</hi> South. About the Equinoctiall ſections, if the declination encreaſe, the Sunne is paſt the ſection: if it decreaſe, it is not come to it, and ſo you may know certainly vnto which quadrant the declination belongeth. You may finde whether the Starre you obſerue, declineth North or South, thus: Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue two Starres, of which by marking the ſituation of Charies wayne, and the Pole ſtarre, you may determine the more Southerly, or the more Northerly: then if you finde their declinations equall, the more Southerly hath South declination, and the more Northerly, North de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination: but if they be vnequall, the more Southerly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſſe, it declineth Southward: but if it haue the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter declination, the more Northerly declineth North, which is to be vnderſtoode of obſeruations taken on this Northſide of the Equinoctiall: but you may make this doctrine generall, thus: If that which is neereſt the bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13856:19"/>pole be leſſe, it declineth toward that pole: if greater, then that, which is néerer the apparant pole, declineth toward the apparant pole. This diſtiction ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be preciſely obſerued hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The eight Concluſion.</hi> The declination of the Sunne, or any Starre being giuen, together with the Azimute and anie height, to finde the Meridian height.</head>
                  <p>LEt the circumferences <hi>E F, C G,</hi> be made either of them equall to the height giuen, and laying a ruler on <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> it will cut <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>P:</hi> make the circumference <hi>E X</hi> equall to <hi>E F,</hi> and laying a ruler on <hi>P</hi> and <hi>X,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>Y:</hi> vpon <hi>Y,</hi> as a center, at the diſtance <hi>Y A,</hi> deſcribe a ſemicircle <hi>R V A</hi> (a ſemicircle thus deſeribed, hauing one angle in the center <hi>A,</hi> and the Diameter equall to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiameter of another circle, as <hi>R A</hi> equall to <hi>F P,</hi> which is the ſemidiameter of the circle, whoſe Diameter is the diſtance <hi>F G</hi>) this ſemicircle ſhall be called the Synicall arch of that line, or diſtance, as <hi>R V A</hi> is the Synical arch of the diſtance <hi>F G.</hi> Let the diſtance of the Azimute from the Eaſt, and that in this figure Southward, be the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference <hi>E W:</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>W,</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the ſemicircle <hi>R V A</hi> in <hi>V,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>R V,</hi> and ſetting one foote of your Compaſſe in <hi>P,</hi> with the other in the line <hi>P F,</hi> marke a poynt <hi>O.</hi> Now let <hi>K L</hi> be the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the Sunnes parallel, and diuide <hi>K L</hi> ſo in <hi>O,</hi> as the greater ſegment <hi>O L</hi> may be to <hi>O G,</hi> the greater ſeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>F G,</hi> as <hi>F O,</hi> the leſſer ſegment of <hi>F G,</hi> is to the leſſer ſegment <hi>K O</hi> (how this may be done ſhall be taught hereafter:) then opening your Compaſſe to the length of the ſegment lying toward the quadrant <hi>E F B,</hi> as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>O K,</hi> ſet one foote in <hi>O,</hi> and with the other marke in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13856:20"/>the quadrant <hi>E F B</hi> the poynt <hi>K,</hi> the circumference <hi>E K</hi> is the Meridian height.</p>
                  <div type="corollary">
                     <head>A Lemma.</head>
                     <p>Betwéene <hi>F O</hi> and <hi>O G,</hi> by <hi>13. P. 6.</hi> take a meane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionall <hi>H N,</hi> and to that meane proportional giuen, in <hi>K L</hi> finde the two extremes, <hi>K O, O L,</hi> by the addition of <hi>Peletarius</hi> to <hi>13. P. 6.</hi> but in the Engliſh Euclyde the figure is drawne wrong, &amp; the demonſtration diſtorted: you may helpe your ſelfe in the ſame author, where <hi>17. p. 10.</hi> you haue out of <hi>Campane</hi> the ſame matter truly propounded.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ninth Concluſion.</hi> In any Countrie vnknowne, two different heights with the Azimutes of the Sunne, or any knowne Star being giuen, to finde their Meridian height, and declination.</head>
                  <p>LEt the two heights giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>E H,</hi> make <hi>C G</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>C I</hi> equall to <hi>E H,</hi> draw the lines <hi>F G,</hi> and <hi>A I,</hi> cutting <hi>A B</hi> in the poynts <hi>P</hi> &amp; <hi>N:</hi> let the ſemicircle <hi>R V A</hi> be the Synicall arch to <hi>F G,</hi> and <hi>S T A,</hi> the Synical arch to <hi>H I.</hi> Moreouer, let <hi>E W</hi> be the diſtance of the Azi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute, belonging to the height <hi>E F,</hi> from the Eaſt South, and <hi>E X,</hi> the diſtance of the Azimute, belonging to the height <hi>E H:</hi> likewiſe from the Eaſt South, a ruler layd on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>W,</hi> will cut the ſemicircle <hi>R V A</hi> in <hi>V:</hi> take the diſtance <hi>R V,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>P,</hi> with the other in <hi>P F</hi> marke <hi>O:</hi> againe, laying a ruler on <hi>X</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> it wil cut the ſemicircle <hi>S T A</hi> in <hi>T:</hi> take the diſtance <hi>S T,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>N,</hi> with the other in the line <hi>N H,</hi> marke a poynt <hi>M:</hi> vpon <hi>M</hi> and <hi>O</hi> laying a ruler, draw the line <hi>K M O L,</hi> which is the Diameter for the parallel of decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, whereby you may know the declination, and <hi>E K</hi> is the Meridian height.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13856:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The tenth Concluſion.</hi> The Meridian height &amp; declination of the Sunne, or any Starre being giuen, to finde the latitude.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt you muſt know whether the height be Northerly or Southerly, which <hi>Nonnius</hi> thinketh the magnetical Index, or Compaſſe will ſhewe readily, and exactly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough:
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13856:21"/>
                     <hi>Clauius</hi> determineth of it, by marking on what hand the riſing or Eaſt ſide of the Horizon is: but in the night it may be certainely knowne, by looking vpon the ſtarres about the North pole, then muſt you marke, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after the height taken, the Starre grow higher, or lower. Now let the Meridian height being Southward and higheſt, be <hi>E K,</hi> from <hi>K</hi> towards the pole, which the declination reſpecteth not, as if the declination be North, then South ward: if South, then Northward: and here ſuppoſing the declination Northward, from <hi>K</hi> towards <hi>E,</hi> if muſt be taken, as <hi>K Z,</hi> the circumference <hi>Z K B</hi> is the latitude, if the height bad béene loweſt, the declination ſhould have béene taken at the other ende of the parallels Diameter, betwéene <hi>B</hi> and <hi>C,</hi> for ſo it ſhould haue béene aboue the Horizon wholy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The eleuenth Concluſion.</hi> The declination of the Sunne or any knowne Starre being giuen, in a Countrie of knowne latitude, to find the Meridian height.</head>
                  <p>IF the complement of the Starres declination, or the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Pole be leſſe then the latitude, there be two Meridian heightes, one higheſt, and the other loweſt. Let the latitude giuen, be <hi>K Z,</hi> and let the declination be <hi>Z K,</hi> opening your Compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>B C,</hi> kéepe one foote in <hi>B,</hi> and with the other towards <hi>K,</hi> marke in the lymbe the point <hi>E,</hi> the circumference <hi>E Z K,</hi> is the Meridian height.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The twelfth Concluſion.</hi> The Meridian height of the Sunne, or any Starre being giuen, in a Countrie of knowne latitude, to finde the Declination.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>E K</hi> be the Meridian height, opening your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the latitude giuen, ſet one foote in <hi>B,</hi> and with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13856:21"/>the other from the pole, marke in the lymbe the point <hi>Z: Z K</hi> is the declination ſought for, taking denomination of that Pole, betwéene which, and <hi>Z,</hi> it is placed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The thirteenth Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of knowne latitude, the declination, and height of the Sunne or any knowne Starre being giuen, to finde the Azimute.</head>
                  <p>LEt the height giuen be <hi>E H,</hi> make the circumference <hi>C I</hi> equall to <hi>E H,</hi> and draw the lyne <hi>H I,</hi> and let <hi>S T A</hi> be Synicall arch of the lyne <hi>H I,</hi> let the latitude gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be <hi>B Z,</hi> vpon <hi>Z</hi> and <hi>A</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe on the other ſide in <hi>Q,</hi> make eyther of the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences <hi>Z K, Q L</hi> equall to the declination giuen, and laying a ruler on <hi>K</hi> and <hi>L,</hi> it will cut <hi>N H</hi> in <hi>M:</hi> with your compaſſe take the diſtance <hi>N M,</hi> and ſetting one foot in <hi>S,</hi> in the ſemicircle <hi>S T A</hi> take with the other foot a point <hi>T,</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>T</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe in <hi>X:</hi> the circumference <hi>E X</hi> is the diſtance of the Azimute from Eaſt, or Weſt: Southward, becauſe <hi>M</hi> fell in the quadrant <hi>B Z E,</hi> whereas if it had fallen in the quadrant <hi>B I C,</hi> it ſhould haue béene Northward, whether it be to be accompted from Eaſt or Weſt, the riſing in height, or decreaſing will ſhew.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourteenth Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of knowne latitude, the Azimute and declination of the Sunne, or any Starre beeing giuen, to finde the height.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>K L</hi> be the Diameter of the parallell of decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, cutting <hi>A B</hi> axis of the Horizon in <hi>Q,</hi> and let <hi>B D,</hi> be equall to the Azimutes diſtance from the Eaſt, or Weſt towards the South taken in the quadrant <hi>B E,</hi> if it were Northward, it were to be taken in the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13856:22"/>quadrant <hi>B C:</hi> betwéene <hi>D</hi> and <hi>B</hi> take any point <hi>1,</hi> and make the circumference <hi>D 3</hi> equall to <hi>1 B,</hi> laying a ruler vpon <hi>3</hi> and <hi>1,</hi> draw the line <hi>2 O,</hi> then making <hi>A P</hi> equall
<figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> to <hi>2 O,</hi> vpon <hi>O</hi> and <hi>P,</hi> laying a ruler, draw the line <hi>P O F,</hi> a ruler layd on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>D,</hi> will cut <hi>O 2 4:</hi> in <hi>P F</hi> take a line <hi>P 6,</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>A 4,</hi> then laying a ruler
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13856:22"/>vpon <hi>Q</hi> and <hi>6,</hi> it will cut the lymbe in <hi>H,</hi> the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>E F H</hi> is the height deſired. In ſome caſes this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction will not be contayned within the lymbe, but it is generally true.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fifteenth Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of knowen latitude the Azimute, and height of the Sunne, or any Starre being giuen, to finde the declination.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>B Z</hi> be the latitude giuen, and let the altitude be <hi>E H,</hi> make <hi>C I</hi> equall to <hi>E H,</hi> and drawe the line <hi>H I,</hi> cutting <hi>A B,</hi> in <hi>N:</hi> let the diſtance of the Azimute from the Eaſt be <hi>E X;</hi> and let <hi>S T A</hi> be the Synicall arche of <hi>H I:</hi> now laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>X,</hi> it will cut <hi>S T A</hi> in <hi>T,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>S T,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>N,</hi> with the other in <hi>N H,</hi> becauſe the Azimute is Southward (otherwiſe in <hi>N I</hi>) take a point <hi>M,</hi> vpon <hi>M</hi> and <hi>A</hi> laying a ruler it will cut the limbe in <hi>5,</hi> make <hi>Q 7</hi> equall to <hi>Z 5,</hi> &amp; draw the line <hi>A 7,</hi> make <hi>A 8</hi> equal to <hi>A M,</hi> vpon <hi>M</hi> and <hi>8,</hi> laying a ruler, draw the lyne <hi>K M 8 L,</hi> the circumference <hi>Z K,</hi> or <hi>Q L,</hi> is the declination ſought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſixteenth Concluſion.</hi> The Sunnes declination being giuen, to finde his place in the Zodiacke.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>E H</hi> be the Sunnes greateſt declination, <hi>videl.</hi> as I ſaid in the firſt ſection, to be receiued vpon their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, which by obſeruation made with large inſtruments, affirme it in this our age to be <hi>23.</hi> degrées, <hi>30.</hi> minutes: draw the line <hi>A H,</hi> and let eyther of the circumferences, <hi>E F, C G,</hi> be equall to the declination giuen, vpon <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut <hi>A H</hi> in <hi>K:</hi> in <hi>E M A</hi> the Synicall arche of the lymbe, apply from <hi>E</hi> at <hi>M</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>A K,</hi> vpon <hi>M</hi> and <hi>A</hi> lay a ruler, which will cut the lymbe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13856:23"/>in <hi>O,</hi> a circumference taken in the quadrante, to which the declination belongeth, from the next Equinoctiall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, equall to <hi>E O,</hi> as <hi>E O</hi> in the quadrante <hi>D E,</hi> ſheweth the place of the Sunne, accounting from <hi>E,</hi> the beginning of <hi>Aries</hi> by <hi>B</hi> and <hi>C,</hi> to <hi>O.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſeuenteenth Concluſion.</hi> Another way to finde the Sunnes place by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination giuen.</head>
                  <p>VPon <hi>I,</hi> and <hi>H,</hi> the Sunnes greateſt declination rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned from <hi>E,</hi> and <hi>C,</hi> lay a ruler, which will cut the line <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>P,</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> as a center, at the diſtance <hi>A P,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe a circle <hi>Q P R:</hi> now let either of the circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> be equall to the declination giuen, vpon <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G</hi> lay a ruler, which will cut the circle <hi>Q A R</hi> in <hi>S,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe on the other ſide in <hi>W,</hi> but imagining the declination to appertaine to the Quadrant <hi>E H B,</hi> take <hi>S,</hi> the point in it, and vpon <hi>S</hi> and <hi>A</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe in <hi>T,</hi> reckoning from <hi>E</hi> the beginning of <hi>Aries</hi> to <hi>T,</hi> you haue the Sunnes place you ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The eighteenth Concluſion.</hi> The Sunnes place in the Zodiacke being giuen, to finde his declination.</head>
                  <p>FRom <hi>E</hi> towardes <hi>D</hi> take a circumference <hi>E O</hi> equall to the Sunnes diſtance from the Equinoctiall ſection, that is neareſt to his place, and let <hi>E M A</hi> be the Synicall arche of the limbe, <hi>E H, C I</hi> equall to the Sunnes grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt declination, and drawe the lines <hi>H A, A I,</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>A,</hi> and <hi>O,</hi> it will cut <hi>E M A</hi> in <hi>M:</hi> make <hi>A K</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>E M,</hi> and <hi>A V</hi> equall to <hi>A K,</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>K</hi> and <hi>V,</hi> it will cut the limbe in <hi>F,</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> eyther of the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G,</hi> are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:13856:23"/>
               <div n="19" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The nineteenth Concluſion.</hi> Another way to finde the Sunnes declination by his place giuen.</head>
                  <p>VPon <hi>T</hi> the Sunnes place, and <hi>A</hi> lay a ruler, which will cut the circle <hi>Q P R</hi> in <hi>S:</hi> make the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>R W,</hi> equall to <hi>Q S,</hi> and laying a ruler on <hi>S</hi> and <hi>W,</hi> it will cut the limbe in <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> either of the circumferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>E F,</hi> or <hi>C G</hi> is the declination ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The twentith Concluſion.</hi> The Sunnes declination being giuen, to finde his right Aſcenſion.</head>
                  <p>LEt eyther of the circumferences <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>CG,</hi> be equal to the Sunnes declination giuen, vpon <hi>G,</hi> and <hi>F</hi> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ruler, it will cut <hi>A H</hi> in <hi>K,</hi> and <hi>B A</hi> in <hi>X,</hi> let <hi>Y L A</hi> be the Synicall arche of the diſtance <hi>F G,</hi> and from <hi>Y</hi> to <hi>L</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plite in the Semicircle <hi>Y L A,</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>X K;</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>L</hi> and <hi>A</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the limbe in <hi>N.</hi> In the quadrant, to which the declination belongeth, from the next Equinoctiall ſection, a circumference taken equall to <hi>E N,</hi> as <hi>E N</hi> in the quadrant <hi>E N D,</hi> ſheweth the right aſcenſion from <hi>E</hi> by <hi>B</hi> to <hi>N.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 21. Concluſion.</hi> The right aſcenſion of any point in the Zodiake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giuen, to finde the Meridian angle.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>E O</hi> be equall to the diſtance of the right aſcenſion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the neareſt Equinoctial ſection, vpon <hi>A</hi> &amp; <hi>O</hi> a ruler laid will cut <hi>E M A</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Synical arche of the limbe in <hi>M,</hi> in the lines <hi>H A, A I</hi> take <hi>A K,</hi> and <hi>A V</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>E M,</hi> vpon <hi>K V,</hi> laying a ruler, it wil cut <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>X:</hi> in <hi>Y L A</hi> the Synicall arch of the diſtance <hi>F G</hi> applie at <hi>Z,</hi> from <hi>A</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:13856:24"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> a diſtance equall to <hi>X V,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Z,</hi> cutteth the limbe in <hi>4,</hi> the circumference <hi>E 4</hi> is the Meridian angle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13856:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 22. Concluſion.</hi> The right aſcenſion of the Sunne being giuen, to finde his place in the Zodiacke.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>E O</hi> be equall to the right aſcenſions diſtance from the neareſt Equinoctiall ſection, and make <hi>D 3</hi> equall to <hi>D O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and draw the line <hi>O 3,</hi> let the Meridian angle ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the former concluſion be <hi>E 4,</hi> and make <hi>D 5</hi> equall to <hi>D 4</hi> a ruler laid vpon the points <hi>4</hi> and <hi>5</hi> will cut <hi>A D</hi> in <hi>7,</hi> open your compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>A 7,</hi> and keeping one foot in <hi>A,</hi> with the other towards <hi>3,</hi> in the line <hi>O 3,</hi> marke a point <hi>6,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>6,</hi> cutteth the lymbe in <hi>2,</hi> the circumference <hi>C 2</hi> is equall to the diſtance of the Sunnes place from the Equinoctiall ſection, in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant, wherein the right aſcenſion was.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 23. Concluſion.</hi> The Sunnes right aſcenſion being giuen, to finde his declination.</head>
                  <p>FRom <hi>D</hi> and <hi>B</hi> towardes <hi>E,</hi> take circumferences <hi>D O, B T</hi> equall to the diſtance of the right aſcenſion from the neareſt Equinoctiall ſection, &amp; laying a ruler on <hi>O</hi> and <hi>T,</hi> it will cut the lines <hi>AE, A H</hi> in the points <hi>B</hi> &amp; <hi>Q:</hi> in <hi>A B</hi> take <hi>A D,</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>B Q,</hi> and drawe the line <hi>D C,</hi> in it take a line <hi>C 8,</hi> equall to <hi>C A,</hi> and then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the diſtance <hi>A 8,</hi> ſet one foote of your compaſſe in <hi>E,</hi> and with the other in the quadrant <hi>E B,</hi> marke a point <hi>F,</hi> the circumference <hi>E F,</hi> is the declination ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 24. Concluſion.</hi> The declination of any ſtarre being giuen, with his latitude, which neuer altereth, to finde his longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or place in the Zodiacke.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>L</hi> be the pole of the Zodiacke, <hi>B</hi> the pole of the worlde, and make the circumferences <hi>L H, L I</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13856:25"/>to the complement of the latitude giuen, that is, let them be equall to that portion of a quadrant, whereby it exceedeth the latitude, draw the line <hi>H I.</hi> Againe let ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> be equall to the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation giuen, a ruler laid vpon <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> will cut <hi>H I</hi> in <hi>K:</hi> againe a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>L,</hi> will cut it in <hi>M:</hi> with your compaſſe take the diſtance <hi>M K,</hi> &amp; in the ſemicircle <hi>6 N A,</hi> which is the Synicall arch for the line <hi>H I,</hi> from <hi>6</hi> apply at <hi>N</hi> a diſtance equal to <hi>M K,</hi> a ruler laid vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> points <hi>A N,</hi> will cut the limbe in <hi>O:</hi> a diſtance equal to <hi>E O,</hi> applyed in the quadrant <hi>C D,</hi> to which I ſuppoſe the declination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, from <hi>C</hi> the Equinoctiall ſection, vnto <hi>P,</hi> ſheweth in the Zodiacke from <hi>E</hi> by <hi>B</hi> to <hi>P</hi> the place of the ſtarre.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 25. Concluſion.</hi> The declination of any ſtarre being giuen, with his latitude, which neuer altereth, to finde the right Aſcenſion thereof.</head>
                  <p>AS before let <hi>L</hi> be the pole of the Zodiacke, <hi>B,</hi> the pole of the world, <hi>L I, L H,</hi> the complements of the ſtarres latitude, <hi>E F, CG,</hi> equall to the declination, draw the line <hi>H I,</hi> and lay a ruler on <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> which will cut <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>Q,</hi> and <hi>H I</hi> in <hi>K;</hi> let the ſemicircle <hi>A R S</hi> be the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall arch for the diſtance <hi>F G,</hi> and from <hi>S</hi> in the ſemicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <hi>A R S,</hi> applie at <hi>R</hi> a diſtance equall to the diſtance <hi>Q K,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>R</hi> &amp; <hi>A,</hi> will cut the limbe in <hi>T,</hi> the diſtance, <hi>C T,</hi> in the quadrant, to which the declination belongeth, applied from the Equinoctiall ſection, ſheweth in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall the right aſcenſion ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 26. Concluſion.</hi> The longitude and latitude of any ſtarre being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to finde the declination and right Aſcenſion thereof.</head>
                  <p>LEt the poles &amp; latitude be as before, &amp; let <hi>E O</hi> be equal to the diſtance of the ſtars place from the neareſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13856:25"/>ſection: a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>O,</hi> will cut the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference <hi>6 N A,</hi> which is the ſynical arch to the line <hi>H I,</hi> in the point <hi>N;</hi> againe a ruler laide on <hi>A</hi> &amp; <hi>I,</hi> will cut <hi>H I</hi> in <hi>M,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>6 N,</hi> &amp; ſetting one foote in <hi>M,</hi> with the other towards <hi>I,</hi> if the place be nearer the pole <hi>B,</hi> or towards <hi>H,</hi> if nearer <hi>D,</hi> but here ſuppoſing it nearer <hi>B,</hi> in <hi>M I</hi> marke <hi>K,</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>K</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the limbe in <hi>V,</hi> make the circumference <hi>B W</hi> equal to <hi>B V,</hi> and draw the line <hi>A W,</hi> and in it make <hi>A X</hi> equall to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>A K,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>X</hi> and <hi>K,</hi> will cut the lymbe in <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> and the line <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>Q,</hi> eyther of the circumferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>E F, C G</hi> is equall to the declination. Now in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micircle <hi>S R A,</hi> which is the Sinicall arch for the diſtance <hi>F G,</hi> apply a diſtance equall to <hi>Q K</hi> from <hi>S</hi> to <hi>R:</hi> vpon <hi>A,</hi> and <hi>R</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe in <hi>T,</hi> the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference <hi>C T,</hi> is the diſtance of the right aſcenſion, from the Equinoctiall ſection, taken in the quadrant, to which the longitude belongeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 27. Concluſion.</hi> The declination and right aſcenſion of any ſtarre being giuen, to finde the longitude and latitude thereof.</head>
                  <p>THis differeth not in working from the former, onelie change the names, let <hi>L</hi> be the pole of the worlde, <hi>B</hi> the pole of the Zodiacke, <hi>H I</hi> ioyneth the complements of the declination giuen, <hi>E O</hi> is equall to the diſtance of the right aſcenſion, from the neareſt Equinoctiall ſection, <hi>6 N A</hi> the Synicall arch for <hi>H I,</hi> is cut in <hi>N</hi> by a ruler laid on <hi>O</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> make <hi>M K</hi> equall to <hi>6 N,</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>K</hi> a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler laid cutteth the limbe in <hi>V,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> circumferences <hi>B V, B W</hi> being equall, and the liue <hi>A W</hi> drawen, <hi>A X</hi> muſt be made equall to <hi>A K,</hi> a ruler lying on <hi>X</hi> and <hi>K</hi> cutteth the limbe in <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> ſo either of the circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13856:26"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> to the latitude ſought for. In the Synicall arch of <hi>F G,</hi> which is <hi>A R S,</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>M K</hi> applyed from <hi>S</hi> to <hi>R,</hi> and then a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>R,</hi> cutteth the limbe in <hi>T,</hi> ſo is <hi>C T</hi> the diſtance of the longitude, from the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Equinoctiall ſection taken in the quadrant, to which the right aſcenſion belongeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:13856:26"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 28. Concluſion.</hi> The longitudes and latitudes of any two ſtarres, or any two places in the earth being giuen, to finde the diſtance of the one from the other.</head>
                  <p>IF they be both on one ſide of the Equinoctiall, or of the Eclipticke what caſe ſoeuer fall out, you ſhall take their latitudes, as heights aboue the Horizon, and the difference of their longitudes, as the diſtance of their Azimutes; by which working, after the <hi>5.</hi> Concluſion, you ſhall finde their diſtance: but if one be on the one ſide of the Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiall, and the other on the other, or, of the Eclipticke, then if they differ not in longitude, from <hi>E</hi> towardes <hi>B,</hi> take one latitude <hi>E L,</hi> and make <hi>L K</hi> equall to the other lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the circumference <hi>E K</hi> in the Equinoctiall ſheweth their diſtance. If they differ in longitude a whole ſemicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, from <hi>E</hi> towards <hi>D</hi> take <hi>E M</hi> one latitude, and laying a ruler on <hi>M</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> it will cut the limbe on the other ſide in <hi>6,</hi> take <hi>61,</hi> the other latitude, and from <hi>E</hi> to <hi>1,</hi> in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall, you ſhall finde the diſtance: but let the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the longitudes be <hi>E H;</hi> and drawe the line <hi>A H,</hi> let the circumference <hi>F E</hi> be equall to the greater latitude, <hi>H I</hi> to the leſſe, then making <hi>E G</hi> equall to <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>H K</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to <hi>H I,</hi> vpon <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G</hi> a ruler laide, will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>N,</hi> likewiſe laide on <hi>I K,</hi> it will cut <hi>H A</hi> in <hi>P.</hi> In the line <hi>A B</hi> take <hi>A Q</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>N P,</hi> and in <hi>A C</hi> make <hi>A S</hi> equall to <hi>F N,</hi> and <hi>S W</hi> equall to <hi>I P,</hi> in the quadrant <hi>C D</hi> from <hi>C</hi> vnto <hi>3</hi> applie a diſtance equall to <hi>Q W,</hi> the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference <hi>C 3,</hi> is the diſtance ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 29. Concluſion.</hi> The Latitudes and diſtance of any two Starres, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny two places in the Earth being giuen, to finde the difference of their Longitudes.</head>
                  <p>LEt the places firſt be on the one ſide of the eclipticke, or the Equinoctiall, and let the diſtance giuen be <hi>C 4,</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:13856:27"/>let the greater Latitude be <hi>E F,</hi> the leſſer <hi>E L;</hi> make the Circumferences <hi>E G</hi> equall to <hi>EF,</hi> and <hi>E M</hi> equall to <hi>E L,</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>N,</hi> and laide vpon <hi>L</hi> and <hi>M,</hi> it will cut it in <hi>O,</hi> make <hi>A S</hi> equall to <hi>N F,</hi> and <hi>S V</hi> equall to <hi>L O,</hi> then opening your compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>C 4,</hi> ſet one foote in <hi>V,</hi> and with the other marke <hi>Q</hi> in the line <hi>A B,</hi> taking the diſtance <hi>A Q,</hi> ſet one foote in <hi>N,</hi> and with the other deſcribe an arch at <hi>P,</hi> then opening your compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>A O,</hi> and kéeping one foote in <hi>A,</hi> with the other croſſe the arche at <hi>P,</hi> a ruler laide on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>P,</hi> cutteth the limbe in <hi>H,</hi> the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>E H</hi> is the difference of their Longitudes; when the Circumferences méete in the line <hi>A,</hi> they differ not in Longitude, otherwiſe the conſtruction is generall in this caſe. But if one be on the one ſide, and the other on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then muſt you make <hi>S W</hi> equall to <hi>L O,</hi> and opening your compaſſe to the diſtance giuen, which ſuppoſe were <hi>C 3,</hi> ſet one foote in <hi>W,</hi> and with the other, in the line <hi>A B,</hi> marke the poynt <hi>Q,</hi> and then on <hi>N,</hi> as a Center at the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>A Q,</hi> deſcribe an arch at <hi>P,</hi> which being croſſed with another arch, deſcribed vpon the Center <hi>A,</hi> at the diſtance <hi>A O,</hi> a line drawne from <hi>A</hi> by <hi>P</hi> to <hi>H,</hi> ſheweth <hi>E H,</hi> the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of their Longitudes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 30. Concluſion.</hi> The Longitudes and Latitudes of any two Starres, or any two places in the Earth being giuen, to finde the angle of Poſition, or the bearing of the one from the other.</head>
                  <p>BY the Longitudes and Latitudes you may finde the diſtance, and firſt let both the Latitudes be on the one ſide of the Eclipticke, or the Equinoctiall, &amp; their diſtance leſſe then a Quadrant, as <hi>B L,</hi> and <hi>E F</hi> the Latitude of the place from which the other beareth; the complement of the other place whoſe poſition is ſought <hi>C 4,</hi> make <hi>E G</hi> equall
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13856:27"/>to <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>E M</hi> equall to <hi>E L,</hi> which is the complement of the diſtance <hi>B L,</hi> that is giuen: laying a ruler on <hi>G</hi> and <hi>F,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>N,</hi> in <hi>A C</hi> take a line <hi>A S</hi> equall to <hi>F N,</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>L</hi> and <hi>M,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>O,</hi> make <hi>S V</hi> equall to <hi>L O.</hi> Now take the diſtance <hi>C 4,</hi> which is the complement of the Latitude belonging to the other place, and ſetting one foote in <hi>V,</hi> with the other marke in <hi>A B,</hi> a poynte <hi>Q.</hi> taking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtance <hi>A Q.</hi> ſet one foote of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe in <hi>N,</hi> and with the other make an arch at <hi>P,</hi> then vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>A</hi> as a center, at the diſtance <hi>A O,</hi> deſcribe an arch at <hi>P,</hi> croſſing the former, a ruler layde on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>P,</hi> will cut the limbe in <hi>H,</hi> and ſo <hi>E H</hi> is the angle of poſition ſought for. But if the diſtance be greater then a Quadrant, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <hi>D L,</hi> then making <hi>E M</hi> equall to <hi>L E,</hi> the exceſſe of the diſtance aboue a Quadrant, vpon <hi>L</hi> and <hi>M</hi> lay a ruler, which will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>O,</hi> then hauing taken in <hi>A C,</hi> a line <hi>A S</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>F N,</hi> take alſo in <hi>S C</hi> a line <hi>S W</hi> equall to <hi>L O,</hi> and the other Latitude being <hi>D 3,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>C 3,</hi> ſubtended vnder the complement thereof, and ſetting one foote in <hi>W,</hi> with the other marke in the line <hi>A B</hi> a poynt <hi>Q,</hi> opening your compaſſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtance <hi>A Q,</hi> vpon <hi>N</hi> as a center, deſcribe an arch at <hi>P,</hi> which croſſed with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther arch deſcribed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> center <hi>A,</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſtance <hi>A O,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>A,</hi> and the croſſing at <hi>P,</hi> cutteth from the limbe the circumference <hi>E H,</hi> which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angle of poſition ſought for.</p>
                  <p>But now let one Latitude be on the one ſide, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the other of the Eclipticke, or Equinoctiall, and let the diſtance be leſſe then a quadrant, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt you take the lines <hi>A S,</hi> and <hi>S V,</hi> as in the firſt caſe, but in ſtéed of <hi>C 4,</hi> the complement of the other Latitude <hi>D 4,</hi> you muſt take <hi>E D 4,</hi> compounded of the Latitude <hi>D 4,</hi> and the Quadrant <hi>E D,</hi> and opening your compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>E 4,</hi> ſet one foote in <hi>V,</hi> then take a poynt in <hi>A B,</hi> and ſo proſecute the conſtruction as in the firſt caſe.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13856:28"/>
               <div n="31" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 31. Concluſion.</hi> The Latitude of one Starre, or one place in the Earth being giuen, with the diſtance, and angle of poſition, or bearing towards another, to finde the Latitude of this other, and the difference of their Longitudes.</head>
                  <p>LEt the angle of Poſition be equall to the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>H E,</hi> and let the Latitude giuen be <hi>E F,</hi> and the diſtance being leſſe then a Quadrant, let his complement be <hi>H I,</hi> make the Circumference <hi>E G</hi> equall to <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>H K</hi> equall to <hi>H I,</hi> a ruler laide on <hi>F,</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>N:</hi> againe laying a ruler on <hi>I</hi> and <hi>K,</hi> it will cut <hi>A H</hi> in in <hi>P,</hi> in the line <hi>A B</hi> take <hi>A Q,</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>N P,</hi> and in <hi>A C</hi> take a diſtance equall to <hi>Q V,</hi> which being leſſe then a Quadrant, is the Latitude of the other Starre or place, and on the ſame ſide of the Eclipticke, or Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall that the former Latitude is: but if it had been grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then a Quadrant as <hi>E D 4,</hi> then ſhould <hi>D 4</hi> the exceſſe aboue a Quadrant, be the Latitude ſought for, and on the other ſide of the Eclipticke, or Equinoctiall: thus hauing the two Latitudes by them and the diſtance giuen, you may finde the difference of their Longitudes.</p>
                  <p>But if the diſtance be greater then a Quadrant, as <hi>6 B H</hi> is, then muſt you take <hi>H I,</hi> the exceſſe of it, aboue the Quadrant <hi>I B 6,</hi> and making <hi>H K</hi> equall to <hi>H I,</hi> and <hi>E G</hi> equall to <hi>F E,</hi> the Latitude giuen, lay a ruler on <hi>F G,</hi> which will cut the line <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>N,</hi> and on <hi>I K,</hi> which will cut <hi>A H</hi> in <hi>P,</hi> then make <hi>A Q</hi> equall to <hi>N P,</hi> and <hi>A S</hi> equall to <hi>F N,</hi> and <hi>S W</hi> equall to <hi>I P,</hi> then in the lymbe from <hi>C,</hi> applie at <hi>3</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>W Q,</hi> the Circumference <hi>C 3,</hi> being leſſe then a Quadrant, the Complement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>D 3,</hi> is the Latitude ſought for: but if it be greater then a Quadrant, as <hi>E D 3,</hi> then is <hi>D 3</hi> the exceſſe of it aboue a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13856:29"/>Quadrant, the Latitude ſought, but on the ſide contrarie to the Latitude giuen, as it was on the ſame ſide being leſſe then a Quadrant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="note">
                  <head>Adnotandum.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PTolomey</hi> in the firſt booke of his Geographie, <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> promiſeth with his <hi>Meteoroſcopium,</hi> by the Latitudes of two places giuen, and the angle of Poſition to finde the difference of their Longitude, which as <hi>Nonnius</hi> hath truly noted, cannot poſſibly by any inſtrument be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, no nor by any tables, though <hi>Regiomontanus Tabul. prim. mob. Prop. 46.</hi> hath vndertaken it: this <hi>31.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion expreſſeth a generall truth, and <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>de Meteoroſc.</hi> quite digreſſing from <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mey,</hi> hath in like manner expreſſed it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="note">
                  <head>A Caution.</head>
                  <p>IN theſe foure laſt Concluſions, following the conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here ſet downe, the circle will not be ſufficient to containe the lines required, which you may helpe by the Synicall arch of the lymbe, applying your lines in the limbe from the concourſe thereof and the Synicall arch, it would be too tedious to exemplifie all particulars, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for your better vnderſtanding I will onely ſet down for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 32. Concluſion.</hi> Another way to finde the diſtance of two Starres, or places in the Earth, hauing their Latitudes, and the difference of their Longitudes giuen.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Semicircle <hi>A B C</hi> be the Synicall arch of the lymbe, and from the concourſe of it and the lymbe <hi>C,</hi> applie at <hi>7</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>N P,</hi> a ruler laide on <hi>C</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:13856:29"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> and <hi>7</hi> will cut the Semicircle <hi>A B C</hi> in <hi>Z,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>C Z,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>A,</hi> with the other in the line <hi>A B</hi> marke a poynt <hi>X,</hi> againe making <hi>A S</hi> equall to <hi>F N,</hi> and <hi>S V</hi> equall to <hi>I P,</hi> applie from <hi>C</hi> to <hi>D</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>V A,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>C D</hi> will cut <hi>A B C</hi> in <hi>Y,</hi> make <hi>T V</hi> equall to <hi>C Y,</hi> and from <hi>C</hi> in the arch <hi>A B C</hi> applie at <hi>B</hi> a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13856:30"/>diſtance equall to <hi>T X,</hi> a ruler layd on <hi>C B</hi> will cut the limbe in <hi>4,</hi> the Circumference <hi>C 4</hi> is the diſtance ſought for: the other caſes may be all handled after this faſhion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 33. Concluſion.</hi> The longitudes and latitudes of any three Starres, or any three places in the earth being giuen, to knowe whether they bee in one greateſt circle or no.</head>
                  <p>TAke the diſtance betwéene the firſt and the middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, which let be <hi>E L,</hi> &amp; likewiſe betwéen the middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt and the third, which let be <hi>L I,</hi> and let the diſtance betwéene the firſt and the third be <hi>E G,</hi> now if <hi>E G</hi> be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to <hi>E I</hi> they be in one greateſt circle, otherwiſe not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 34. Concluſion.</hi> Any vnknowne ſtarre being ſeene, to find the right aſcenſion and declination of it.</head>
                  <p>HAuing thriſe obſerued the Azimute, and Almicantar or height, you may by the ſeauenth concluſion finde the declination of it, then take the diſtance of it, from any knowen ſtarre, by the declinations taken as latitudes and their diſtance, you may finde the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their right aſcenſions, as the difference of their longitudes, which added or ſubſtracted accordingly from the knowen ſtarres right Aſcenſion, yéeldeth the right Aſcenſion of the vnknowen Starre. <hi>Gemma Friſius</hi> his chapter anſwering this concluſion, includeth Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metes, but their <hi>Parallaxis</hi> being neglected, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth not, neither his working nor this concluſion, no leſſe exact then his working, can duelie performe that hée propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth. In the Moon beſides her Parallar, the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13856:30"/>of her motion, will be alſo a let, although <hi>Ptolomeye Almag. lib. 7. c. 2. Regiomontanus</hi> in <hi>Epit.</hi> and <hi>Copernicus lib. 1. c. vlt.</hi> by their Aſtrolabe or <hi>Armillae</hi> which <hi>Pappus Comment</hi> in <hi>5. Alm.</hi> calleth <hi>Meteoroſcopion,</hi> take the place of the Moone to finde the longitude of the ſtars, and peraduenture the methode vſed of <hi>Copernicus lib. 2. c. 2.</hi> is fitter for that purpoſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 35. Concluſion.</hi> The latitude or amplitude of the Sunnes or anie knowne Starres riſing being giuen with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, to knowe the height of the Pole.</head>
                  <p>ON the land it is caſie to marke in what points of the Horizon the Sunne or any ſtarre riſeth and ſetteth, and it is a common practiſe at Sea, to ſet the Compaſſe with the Sunne, at his riſing, and going downe, the halfe of the circumfere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce intercepted betwéen thoſe two points, is the amplitude of riſing, reckoned from the Meridian. In the Sunne about the Equinoctiall ſections ſome little errour may happen, which although <hi>M. Digges</hi> in <hi>Scal. Mathem.</hi> thinketh worth the correcting, may in handling theſe common inſtruments be nothing regarded. But to the concluſion: let <hi>E F,</hi> and <hi>C G,</hi> be eyther of them equall to the declination giuen, and draw the line <hi>F G,</hi> let the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference <hi>E H,</hi> be equall to the amplitude of riſing, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Eaſt, a ruler laid on <hi>H,</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> will cut <hi>E I A</hi> the Synicall arche of the limbe in <hi>I,</hi> with your Compaſſe take the diſtance <hi>E I,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>A,</hi> with the other toward <hi>G,</hi> or <hi>F,</hi> it ſkilleth not which, take a poynt <hi>K,</hi> a ruler laide on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>K,</hi> will cut the lymbe in <hi>L,</hi> the circumference <hi>B L,</hi> is the height of the pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:13856:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 36. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of knowne Latitude, the declination of the Sunne or any Starre being giuen, to know the amplitude or Latitude of riſing.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> be equall to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination giuen, and <hi>B L</hi> the height of the Pole, a ruler layd on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>L,</hi> will cut <hi>F G</hi> in <hi>K,</hi> in <hi>E I A</hi> the Synicall arch of the lymbe, applie from <hi>E</hi> to <hi>I</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>A K,</hi> and laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> it will cut the lymbe in <hi>H,</hi> the circumference <hi>E H,</hi> is the diſtance of riſing from the Eaſt Northward, if <hi>G F</hi> fall betwéene the Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and the North Pole South ward, if betwéene the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall and the Antarticke Pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 37. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of knowne Latitude, the Amplitude or Latitude of the Sunnes or any Starres riſing being giuen, to finde the Declination.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>B L</hi> be the height of the Pole, and drawe the line <hi>A L,</hi> let the diſtance of the riſing from the Eaſt, be <hi>E H,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>H,</hi> will cut <hi>E I A,</hi> the Synicall arch of the lymbe in <hi>I,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>E I,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>A,</hi> with the other in the line <hi>A L,</hi> marke <hi>K,</hi> then make <hi>B M</hi> equall to <hi>B L,</hi> and draw the line <hi>A M,</hi> in it take <hi>A N,</hi> equall to <hi>A K,</hi> a ruler laide on <hi>N</hi> and <hi>K,</hi> will cut the lymbe in <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G;</hi> either of the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> are the declination ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 38. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude, the declination of the Sunne or any Starre being giuen, to finde the Semidiurnall arch, or halfe the time it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth aboue the Horizon.</head>
                  <p>LEt the height of the Pole be <hi>L B,</hi> either of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences <hi>E F, C G,</hi> equall to the declination giuen,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13856:31"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> drawing the line <hi>G F,</hi> on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>L</hi> lay a ruler, which will cut <hi>G F</hi> in <hi>K,</hi> take the diſtance <hi>O K,</hi> and from <hi>R</hi> in <hi>R P A</hi> the Synicall arch of <hi>G F,</hi> applie at <hi>P</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>O K,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>P,</hi> cutteth the lymbe in <hi>Q,</hi> if the line <hi>F G</hi> be betwéene the Equinoctiall and the apparant pole, the Semidiurnall arch ſhall be <hi>B E Q,</hi> but if it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Equinoctiall and the hidden Pole, the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diurnall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13856:32"/>diurnall arch ſhall be <hi>Q D,</hi> you may eaſilie ſée in the houre circle, what houres they containe.</p>
                  <div type="corollary">
                     <head>A Corollarie.</head>
                     <p>THe poynt <hi>Q.</hi> if the line <hi>G F,</hi> be betwéene the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Pole and the Equinoctiall, ſheweth the time of the riſing: but if it be betwéene the hidden Pole and the Equinoctiall, it ſheweth the ſetting: if from <hi>C</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>D,</hi> you take in the lymbe a diſtance equall to <hi>E Q,</hi> that poynt will ſhew the ſetting, when <hi>F G</hi> is betwéene the apparant Pole and the Equinoctiall, and the riſing, when it is betwéene the hidden Pole and the Equinoctiall.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 39. Concluſion.</hi> The declination and Semidiurnall arch of the Sun, or any Starre being giuen, to finde the height of the Pole.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G,</hi> be equall to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination giuen, and let <hi>B E Q,</hi> or <hi>D Q,</hi> be the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diurnall arch, a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Q</hi> will cut <hi>R P A,</hi> the Synicall arch of the line <hi>G F</hi> in <hi>P,</hi> make <hi>O K</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>R P,</hi> and laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>K,</hi> it will cut the lymbe in <hi>L,</hi> the Circumference <hi>B L</hi> is the height of the Pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 40. Concluſion.</hi> By two knowne Starres, whereof the one is in the Meridian, the other in the Horizon, to knowe the height of the Pole or Latitude.</head>
                  <p>LEt the declination of that which is in the Horizon, be equall to either of the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> draw the line <hi>G F,</hi> cutting the Axis <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>O,</hi> and let <hi>R P A</hi> be the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13856:32"/>Synicall arch of the line <hi>GF,</hi> and let the right aſcenſion of that, which is in the Meridian, be diſtant from the néereſt Equinoctiall ſection, ſo much, as <hi>Q</hi> is from <hi>E;</hi> now laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Q,</hi> it will cut <hi>R P A</hi> the Synicall arch of the line <hi>F G</hi> in <hi>P,</hi> make <hi>O K,</hi> or <hi>ON,</hi> it ſkilleth not which, equall to <hi>R P,</hi> a ruler laid on K and <hi>A,</hi> will cut the lymbe in <hi>L,</hi> the Circumference <hi>B L</hi> is the height of the Pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 41. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude, the height and declination of the Sunne being giuen, to knowe the houre of the day, or what it is a clocke.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> be equall to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the Sunne, and <hi>B L</hi> and <hi>D T</hi> the height of the Pole, make either of the Circumferences <hi>L S, T H,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the height giuen, a ruler layd on <hi>S</hi> and <hi>H,</hi> will cut <hi>F G</hi> in <hi>V,</hi> in <hi>R P A</hi> the Synicall arch of <hi>F G,</hi> applie from <hi>R</hi> to <hi>W,</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>O V,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>W,</hi> will cut the lymbe in <hi>X.</hi> Before Noone the obſeruation being taken, and if the Axis of the world fall betwéene <hi>V</hi> and the Horizon, then in the quadrant <hi>C D,</hi> taking from <hi>C,</hi> a Circumference equal to <hi>EX,</hi> you ſhal haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted forth, but if <hi>V</hi> fall betwéene the Axis and the Horizon, then take in the Quadrant <hi>B C</hi> from <hi>C,</hi> a Circumference equall to <hi>E X,</hi> and the houre ſhall be poynted out. The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation being taken after Noone, you muſt vſe the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drants <hi>E D</hi> and <hi>E B</hi> in like manner.</p>
                  <div type="note">
                     <head>A Caution.</head>
                     <p>BEcauſe when the Sunne draweth néere the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, you cannot perfectlie diſcerne, whether it bée before Noone, or after Noone, you muſt helpe that matter thus. Take two Obſeruations with ſome pretie diſtance betwéene, and if the laſt be greater then the firſt, thou
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13856:33"/>was the firſt before Noone, but if the laſt be leſſer, then was the laſt after Noone.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 42. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude, the Azimute and declination of the Sunne being giuen, to find the houre of the day.</head>
                  <p>BY the Azimute and declination giuen, you may by the <hi>14.</hi> Concluſion finde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the height thereof, that being had by it and the declination you ſhall by the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion finde the hower.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 43. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude, the height and declination of any Starre being giuen, to find the houre of the night.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Circumferences <hi>E F, C G,</hi> be equall to the declination of the Starre, drawe the line <hi>F G,</hi> cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>B A</hi> in <hi>O;</hi> let either of the Circumferences <hi>L B, D T</hi> bee the height of the Pole, and make the Circumferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>L S, T H</hi> equall to the height giuen: on <hi>S</hi> and <hi>H</hi> lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ruler, it will cut <hi>F G</hi> in <hi>V:</hi> in <hi>R W A</hi> applie from <hi>R</hi> to <hi>W,</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>O V;</hi> and laying a ruler on <hi>W</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> you ſhall cut the lymbe in <hi>X,</hi> if the obſeruation <hi>be taken before the Starre come to the Meridian, which you ſhall know by the</hi> caution of the <hi>41.</hi> Concluſion, <hi>then take a Circumference equall to <hi>EX</hi>
                     </hi> on the one or the other ſide of <hi>C,</hi> according to the falling of the poynt <hi>V</hi> ſhewed in the <hi>41.</hi> Concluſion, and ſo ſhall you haue the diſtance of the Starre from the Meridian, or the howre of the Starre, which imagine you finde to be poynted out by <hi>T:</hi> from <hi>T</hi> toward the poynt <hi>E,</hi> take a Circumference
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13856:33"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> 
                     <hi>TEG,</hi> equall to the Starres right aſcenſion, and from <hi>G</hi> towards <hi>B</hi> take a Circumference <hi>G M</hi> equall to the Suns right aſcenſion, a ruler laide on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>M</hi> in the howre cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle poynteth forth the howre.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13856:34"/>
               <div n="44" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 44. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude, the Azimute and declination of any Starre being giuen, to know the houre of the night.</head>
                  <p>THe Azimute and declination being giuen, you may by the fourtéenth Concluſion finde the height, then by the height and declination by the former Concluſion you may finde the houre.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 45. Concluſion.</hi> Any day of the yeare in a Countrey of knowne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, to finde the beginning, continuance, and ende of the <hi>Crepuſculum,</hi> that is, the dawning in the morning, and twy-light in the euening.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>B L</hi> be the height of the Pole, and either of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferences <hi>E F, C G,</hi> equall to the declination of the Sunnes place for the day giuen, draw the line <hi>F G,</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>L</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut <hi>F G</hi> in <hi>K,</hi> and the lymbe on the other ſide in <hi>T:</hi> from <hi>L</hi> and <hi>T</hi> take vnder the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, that is towards <hi>C</hi> and <hi>D,</hi> the Circumferences <hi>L Y, T Z</hi> of eyghtéene degrées apéece, vpon <hi>Z</hi> and <hi>Y</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut <hi>F G</hi> in <hi>2:</hi> in <hi>R P A</hi> the Synicall arch of <hi>F G,</hi> applie from <hi>R</hi> to <hi>P</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>O K,</hi> againe from <hi>R</hi> to <hi>4</hi> applie in <hi>R P A</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>O 2,</hi> now a ruler layd vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>P,</hi> will cut the lymbe in <hi>Q,</hi> but layd on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>4,</hi> will cut it in <hi>6,</hi> the Circumference <hi>Q 6</hi> in the houre circle will ſhew the continuance of the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſculum.</hi> This added to the Sunnes riſing, which you are taught to know by the <hi>38.</hi> Concluſion, Cor. ſheweth, when it beginneth in the morning, and added to the time of his ſetting, ſheweth when it endeth in the euening: I néed not tell that it endeth in the morning with the riſing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13856:34"/>of the Sunne, and beginneth in the euening with his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 46. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude any day in the yeare at any houre aſſigned, to know the height of the Sunne.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>B L</hi> be the height of the Pole, and the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences <hi>E F, C G</hi> equall to the Sunnes declination for the day giuen, and let <hi>E X</hi> be the houres diſtance from ſixe, on <hi>X</hi> and <hi>A</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut <hi>R P A</hi> the Synicall arch of the line <hi>G F,</hi> in <hi>W:</hi> with your compaſſe take the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>R W,</hi> and ſetting one foot in <hi>O,</hi> marke in the line <hi>F G</hi> a point toward <hi>G,</hi> if in the morning it be before ſixe, or in the euening after ſixe, but if it be after ſixe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or before ſixe in the euening, then towards <hi>F,</hi> as here it is ſuppoſed in the morning after ſixe, and therefore let it be <hi>V,</hi> on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>V</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe in <hi>5,</hi> make the circumference <hi>T 7,</hi> equall to <hi>L <hi>5,</hi>
                     </hi> and draw the line <hi>7 A;</hi> in it take a line <hi>A 3</hi> equal to <hi>A V,</hi> and laying a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler on <hi>V 3,</hi> it will cutte the lymbe in <hi>S</hi> and <hi>H,</hi> either of the circumferences <hi>L S,</hi> or <hi>T H</hi> are the height deſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The</hi> 47. <hi>Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of known latitude, for any day of the yeere, to finde in what Azimute the Sunne is in.</head>
                  <p>BY the former concluſion you learned how to finde the height for the time aſſigned, in the <hi>13</hi> concluſion was taught by the height and declination giuen in a countrie of knowne latitude to finde the Azimute, and ſo by theſe two concluſions you may performe that, which is here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:13856:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 48. Concluſion.</hi> In a countrie of knowne Latitude any day of the yeare at any houre aſſigned, to know how far any determinate point is diſtant from the Meridian.</head>
                  <p>LEt the houre aſſigned be <hi>M,</hi> and from <hi>M</hi> by <hi>B</hi> Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward take a circumference <hi>M B G</hi> equall to the
<figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:13856:35"/>Sunnes right aſcenſion for the time giuen, againe from <hi>G</hi> by <hi>E</hi> take a circumference <hi>G E T</hi> equall to the right aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the point or ſtarre giuen, the circumference <hi>T D</hi> is the diſtance thereof from the Meridian, which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 49. Concluſion</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude at any houre aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned any day of the yeere, to know the height of any knowne Starre.</head>
                  <p>TAke the diſtance of the point or ſtarre at the time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the Meridian, and ſo conſequently from the houre of ſixe, which let be <hi>E X,</hi> and let <hi>E F, C G</hi> be equall to the ſtarres declination, draw the line <hi>F G,</hi> cutting <hi>A B</hi> in <hi>O,</hi> then vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>X</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut <hi>R W A,</hi> the Synicall arch of <hi>F G,</hi> in <hi>W,</hi> with your compaſſe take the diſtance <hi>R W,</hi> and in the lyne <hi>F G</hi> from <hi>O</hi> towards <hi>G,</hi> if the diſtance from the Meridian be more then ſixe houres, but if leſſe then ſixe houres, as here it is ſuppoſed, then to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>F</hi> take <hi>V O,</hi> equall to <hi>R W,</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>V,</hi> it will cutte the lymbe in <hi>5,</hi> make the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>T 7</hi> equall to <hi>L <hi>5,</hi>
                     </hi> and draw the lyne <hi>7 A,</hi> therein take <hi>A 3</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>A V,</hi> and laying a ruler on <hi>V</hi> and <hi>B,</hi> it will cut the lymbe in the points <hi>F</hi> and <hi>G,</hi> ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the circumferences <hi>E F, C G</hi> is equall to the height you deſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 50. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude at any houre aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned any day of the yeare, to know the Azimute of any knowne Starre.</head>
                  <p>BY the former concluſion you knaw how to finde the height for the time aſſigned, and by the height and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13856:36"/>the <hi>13.</hi> concluſion will teach you to finde the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimute as you deſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 51. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrie of knowne Latitude, to finde the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference Aſcenſional, or the difference of the right and oblique aſcenſion of any poynt of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke or any knowne Starre.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>E W</hi> be the height of the Pole, and let either of the Circumferences <hi>W I,</hi> and <hi>W H</hi> be equall to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the declination giuen, draw the line <hi>HI,</hi> cutting the Horizon <hi>E C</hi> in <hi>Y,</hi> and the Axis of the world <hi>A W</hi> in <hi>4,</hi> let <hi>6 Z A</hi> be the Synicall arch for the line <hi>H I,</hi> and therein from <hi>6</hi> to <hi>Z,</hi> applie a diſtance equall to <hi>4 Y,</hi> vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Z</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe in <hi>5,</hi> the circumference <hi>E <hi>5</hi>
                     </hi> is the difference Aſcenſionall which you require.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 52. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude to finde the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique aſcenſion of any poynt of the Eclipticke, or any knowne Starre.</head>
                  <p>LEt the right aſcenſion of the poynt taken by the <hi>20.</hi> Concluſion, be the Circumference <hi>E B G,</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>E,</hi> the beginning of <hi>Aries,</hi> and the difference aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſionall of the poynt, whoſe line of declination is <hi>H I,</hi> let be <hi>E 5:</hi> now if <hi>H I</hi> be betwéene the apparant Pole and the Equinoctiall, take from <hi>G</hi> towards <hi>E</hi> a Circumference <hi>G 1,</hi> equall to <hi>E 5,</hi> and <hi>E B 1</hi> ſhall be the oblique aſcenſion: but if <hi>H I</hi> be betwéene the Equinoctiall and the hidden Pole, then from <hi>G</hi> towards <hi>C,</hi> take the Circumference <hi>G 3</hi> equall to <hi>E 5,</hi> and then ſhall <hi>E G 3</hi> be the oblique aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion ſought for.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:13856:36"/>
                  <div type="corollary">
                     <head>A Corollary.</head>
                     <p>IF you adde a ſemicircle to the oblique Aſcenſion found, that is, if you lay a ruler on <hi>1,</hi> or <hi>3</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> it will in the oppoſite quadrant <hi>E D,</hi> poynt out the oblique deſcenſion of the poynt, that is oppoſite to the poynt whoſe oblique Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion you looke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="corollary">
                     <head>Another Corollary.</head>
                     <p>YOu may alſo finde the oblique deſcenſion of any point by this Concluſion, if you adde, when here you are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to ſubtract, and ſubtract when you are appoynted to adde.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 53. Concluſion.</hi> The oblique Aſcenſion of any poynt of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, or any knowne Starre being giuen, to finde the Latitude.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>W</hi> be the Pole of the world, <hi>W I</hi> and <hi>W H</hi> the complements of the poynts declination, draw the line <hi>H I,</hi> cutting <hi>A W</hi> the Axis of the world in <hi>4,</hi> and let the difference Aſcenſionall (which you may knowe by comparing of the right and oblique Aſcenſions) be <hi>E 5,</hi> a ruler layde on the Center <hi>A</hi> and <hi>5,</hi> will cut <hi>6 Z A</hi> the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall arche of the line <hi>H I</hi> in <hi>Z,</hi> in the line <hi>H 4,</hi> take <hi>Y 4</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>6 Z;</hi> then laying a ruler vpon <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Y,</hi> it will cut the lymbe in <hi>E,</hi> the Circumference <hi>E W</hi> is the height of the Pole, or the Latitude ſought for.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:13856:37"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 54. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of known Latitude, any day aſſigned to knowe what poynt of the Eclipticke is in the Meridian in the morning.</head>
                  <p>TAke the oblique aſcenſion for that poynt of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, wherein the Sunne is that day which is aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13856:37"/>as for example the poynt <hi>V,</hi> then opening your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe to the diſtance <hi>B C,</hi> ſet one foote in <hi>V,</hi> and with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Weſt towards the Eaſt, or according to the ſucceſſion of the degrées or times of the Equinoctiall marke in the lymbe <hi>T,</hi> that poynt is the poynt of the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall which is in the Meridian: now if by the <hi>22.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion you take the poynt anſwerable to that right aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Eclipticke, it ſhall be the ſame that is in the Meridian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 55. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude any day of the yeere, at any houre aſſigned, to finde what poynt of the Eclipticke is in the Meridian.</head>
                  <p>LEt the right aſcenſion anſwering the degrée of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipticke, which ſerueth the day giuen, be <hi>E B V,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted from <hi>E</hi> the beginning of <hi>Aries,</hi> now take the houre diſtance of the Sunne from the Meridian, which let be <hi>B W:</hi> if the Sunne be not yet come to the Meridian, from <hi>V</hi> towards <hi>C,</hi> or from Weſt towards Eaſt, according to the ſucceſſion of the degrées of the Equinoctiall, take a Circumference <hi>V 7</hi> equall to <hi>B W, 7</hi> ſheweth the poynt of the Equinoctiall, that is in the Meridian, the place of the Zodiacke anſwerable to the right aſcenſion, is alſo in the Meridian with it. But if the Sunne be paſt the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, you muſt take a Circumference equall to <hi>B W,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the ſucceſſion of the Equinoctials degrées, as from <hi>V</hi> the Circumference <hi>B V,</hi> and then the poynt of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, which anſwereth the right Aſcenſion <hi>B,</hi> ſhall be in the Meridian, and the ſame is to be vnderſtoode of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite poynts.</p>
               </div>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:13856:38"/>
               <div n="56" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 56. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude any day of the yeere, to know what time any poynt of the Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, or any knowne Starre riſeth or ſetteth.</head>
                  <p>TAke the oblique Aſcenſion of the poynt, which let be <hi>E B G,</hi> and the right Aſcenſion anſwering the poynt, wherein the Sunne is the day giuen, which let be <hi>E B T,</hi> from the houre of the Sunnes riſing according to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the houre circle, take a Circumference equall to <hi>G T,</hi> and it ſhall poynt out the houre, when the Starre commeth to the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 57. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude to know with what poynt of the Eclipticke, any knowne Starre commeth to the Meridian.</head>
                  <p>TAke the right aſcenſion of the Starre, and then the poynt of the Zodiacke that is anſwerable thereunto, and that ſhall be the poynt wherewith the Starre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Meridian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 58. Concluſion.</hi> The oblique aſcenſion being giuen, to know the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the Equinoctiall ſections in reſpect of the Meridian.</head>
                  <p>LEt the oblique aſcenſion giuen be <hi>E B 1,</hi> with your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe take the diſtance <hi>B C,</hi> and ſetting one foote in <hi>1,</hi> with the other marke a poynt <hi>L,</hi> which is the poynt of the Equinoctiall in the Meridian: now for as much as <hi>E</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Meridian, it is in the Weſt quarter aboue the Horizon, if it had fallen betwéene <hi>L</hi> and <hi>1,</hi> it ſhould haue béen in the Eaſt, the oppoſite ſection is alwaies in the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Quadrant.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:13856:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The 59. Concluſion.</hi> In a Countrey of known Latitude to know the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizontall angle, made by the Section of the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon and Eclipticke in any poynt giuen.</head>
                  <p>TAke the oblique Aſcenſion of the poynt giuen, and by it finde the ſituation of the Equinoctiall ſection. Now
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13856:39"/>if the Section be on the Eaſt ſide of the Meridian, take the complements of the oblique aſcenſion, and the poynt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as Latitudes; the Sunnes greateſt declination is the difference of their Longitudes, and by the <hi>30.</hi> Concluſion ſéeke the Horizontall angle, as the bearing of the oblique aſcenſion from the poynt of the Eclipticke, that is in the Horizon, and ſo haue you the Horizontall angle, but if the Equinoctiall Section be on the Weſt ſide, you muſt take the complements to the oppoſite poynts of the Eclipticke, and oblique aſcenſion, and with them worke by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion as is aforeſaide.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>THere remaineth for perfecting this Section almoſt <hi>20.</hi> Concluſions more, wherof many depend vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this probleme: <hi>viz.</hi> In a Countrey of knowne Latitude, any oblique Aſcenſion being giuen, to finde the poynt of the Eclipticke Coaſcending, which yet I haue not found how to perfourme generally, otherwiſe then by taking ſuch helpe of an <hi>Eleipſis,</hi> as is vſed in the fouretéenth Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: in which manner of working the conſtruction will very often exceede the compaſſe of the lymbe, for which and ſome other cauſes I omitte it and the reſt at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Notwithſtanding if I perceiue hereafter, that thoſe matters be much deſired, they ſhall be adioyned at the next impreſſion: the meane while I muſt intreate the reader to take thus much in good part.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the ſecond Section.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:13856:39"/>
               <head>THE THIRD SEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE NEW HAND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LING OF THE PLANISPHERE; WHICH IS A SVPPLEMENT Organicall.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. 1. To make a Quadrant, whereby you may readiſie know what Degrees and Minutes are contained in any Circumference giuen.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the Center <hi>A,</hi> deſcribe a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant <hi>A B C,</hi> whoſe lymbe you muſt diuide, as the common man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is, into <hi>90.</hi> equall parts or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées, &amp; euery degrée into halfes; in the lymbe take the quantitie of <hi>30.</hi> degrées, which let be <hi>C D,</hi> and drawe the line <hi>A D.</hi> In either of the lines <hi>A D,</hi> or <hi>A C,</hi> take ſome reaſonable diſtance from the lymbe, as <hi>A E,</hi> or <hi>A F;</hi> and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Center <hi>A</hi> at that diſtance, deſcribe the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>F E,</hi> then inlarging your compaſſe a little, deſcribe another Circumference, as you ſée at <hi>F</hi> and <hi>E:</hi> againe, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning your compaſſe ſomewhat larger, deſcribe another Circumference <hi>G H,</hi> then extending or contracting the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of your compaſſe, deſcribe a Circumference néere it, as you ſée at <hi>G H.</hi> In like manner deſcribe two other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferences ſomewhat néere together, and diſtant from
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13856:40"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                     </figure> 
                     <hi>G H,</hi> as you ſée at <hi>I K;</hi> and ſo make betwéene <hi>E C, F D 30</hi> ſuch liſts, as you ſée at <hi>F E, G H</hi> and <hi>I K.</hi> Then take an arch of <hi>59</hi> degrées, which you muſt diuide into <hi>60</hi> equall parts, the ſixtie part of which diuiſion, will diuide two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées into two vnequall parts: take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two degrées next <hi>D,</hi> and from that poynt towards <hi>D,</hi> take a Circumference e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the greater ſegment you made by diuiding <hi>59</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées in <hi>60</hi> parts, and vpon that poynt and the Center <hi>A</hi> laying a ruler, where it cutteth the lyſt next the lymbe, as that beneath <hi>L M</hi> is, drawe a line, diuiding the lyſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13856:40"/>
                     <hi>L M,</hi> and from that deuiſion applie ſo many degrées in order, as the circumference will admit, till you come ſo neare <hi>1,</hi> as you can. Then take <hi>58</hi> degrées, and deuide that circumference into <hi>60</hi> equall parts, the ſixtie part of this deuiſion, falling betwéene two degrées deuideth them into two vnequall parts, againe taking <hi>2</hi> degrées next <hi>D,</hi> from that point towards <hi>D,</hi> take the greateſt portion, and laying a ruler on that point and <hi>A,</hi> where it cutteth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond lyſt from the limbe, draw a line cutting that lyſt, and from that deuiſion marke ſo manie degrées in that lyſt, as the reſidue of the circumference will receiue, then deuide <hi>57</hi> degrées for the third lyſt, <hi>56</hi> for the fourth lyſt, and ſo the degrées in order, till you come to thirtie degrées, and the thirtieth liſt, although if the limbe be deuided into halfe degrées, the thirtieth lyſt, &amp; the deuiſion of thirtie degrées is néedles. Hauing thus deuided <hi>30</hi> lyſtes, in the ſpace without the quadrant to the ſide <hi>A C</hi> draw two parallell lines including two ſpaces, &amp; extend one circumference of euery fift lyſt to the vttermoſt parallell, in the ſpace next the ſide of the quadrant <hi>A C,</hi> at the lyſt next the limbe, ſet one, or <hi>1.</hi> at the next circumference extended from the fift lyſt ſet fiue, or <hi>5</hi> in the ſame ſpace, vnder that which is extended from the tenth, ſet <hi>10,</hi> and ſo increaſing by <hi>5</hi> to thirty, then deſcending in the ſecond ſpace, at the fift liſt, ſet <hi>35,</hi> at the tenth <hi>40,</hi> and ſo in order by <hi>5</hi> to <hi>60:</hi> then may you thus vſe the quadrant.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To finde what degrees and minutes are contained in any circumference giuen.</head>
                     <p>VPon the center <hi>A,</hi> deſcribe in the quadrant <hi>A B C,</hi> an arch <hi>N P O,</hi> hauing <hi>A N,</hi> the ſemidiameter equall to the ſemidiameter of the circumference giuen, &amp; take from it, ſo manie degrées, that you haue a remainder leſſe then thirtie, that is take from it ſo manie times <hi>30</hi> degrées as you can, and if the remainder leſſe then thirty, haue a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13856:41"/>of a degrée greater then halfe a degrée, taking that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines with your compaſſe, ſet one foote in <hi>Q,</hi> and take <hi>Q P</hi> equall to your remainder; then laying a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>P,</hi> marke the lyſt by whoſe deuiſion the edge paſſeth moſt exactlie, then in the vtter ſpace, on the outſide of <hi>A C</hi> telling the numbers anſwering that lyſt, you ſhall haue the number of minutes aboue the iuſt degrées. But if your remainder excéed iuſt degrées by leſſe then halfe a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, then taking that portion with your compaſſe, ſet one foote in <hi>N,</hi> and with the other marke <hi>P,</hi> making <hi>N P</hi> equall to the circumference giuen, then laying a ruler on <hi>A,</hi> &amp; <hi>P,</hi> marke the lyſt whoſe deuiſion is cut by the edge of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and then in the ſpace next <hi>A C</hi> tell the number of that lyſt from the lymbe, the number ſo found is the number of minutes, aboue the iuſt degrées. If the ſemidiameter of the circumference giuen be greater, then the ſemidiameter of the quadrant, vpon the center of the circumference gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, deſcribe another, hauing the ſemidiameter equall to the quadrants ſemidiameter, &amp; laying a ruler on the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the point giuen, marke where it cut the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, hauing the ſemidiameter equal to the quadrants ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiameter, and inſtéed of the circumference giuen, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that circumference into the limbe of the quadrant, and then by it proſecute your conſtruction, as is before ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. Thus may you make one quadrant ſerue inſtéed of many vſed by <hi>Clauius</hi> in his <hi>Gnomonia</hi> and Aſtrolabe, and ſupplie with <hi>30.</hi> diuiſions thoſe <hi>60.</hi> which in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the like quadrant out of <hi>Iacobus Curtius</hi> he appointeth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. 2. To deſcribe a triangle for enlarging or contracting of Scales, and aſſigning any parts, or proportion giuen in any rightline.</head>
                  <p>DRaw o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he out ſide of the quadrant, two lines pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>callell to <hi>A B,</hi> &amp; deuide the outward ſpace into what
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13856:41"/>number of equall partes you will, which you may doe at pleaſure before you deſcribe the limbe of the quadrant, and in the ſpace next <hi>A B</hi> at euery fift deuiſion write <hi>5, 10, 15,</hi> &amp; ſo forth, according to your number of deuiſions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may readily tell from <hi>A,</hi> the parts contained in the deuided ſpace, then drawing the line <hi>D B</hi> you ſhall vſe it thus.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To cut from a right line giuen any part appointed.</head>
                     <p>LEt the partes be theſe, which are contained in <hi>A 2,</hi> and make <hi>A R</hi> equall to <hi>A 2,</hi> draw the line <hi>R 2,</hi> now the line giuen is either greater, or leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>A 2:</hi> firſt ſuppoſe it leſſe, &amp; let it be equall to <hi>R Y,</hi> make <hi>R W</hi> equall to <hi>R Y,</hi> draw the line <hi>W Y,</hi> now laying a ruler on <hi>R</hi> and <hi>1,</hi> one of the parts contained in <hi>A 2,</hi> it will cut <hi>W Y</hi> in <hi>X,</hi> the line <hi>X Y</hi> is contained in the line <hi>W Y,</hi> ſo often, as the line <hi>A 1,</hi> is contained in the line <hi>A 2.</hi> But if the line giuen be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>A 2,</hi> then make <hi>A S</hi> equall vnto it, and <hi>A R</hi> equall to <hi>A 2</hi> contayning the parts aſſigned, draw the lines <hi>2 R,</hi> and in <hi>2 R</hi> take <hi>2 V</hi> equall to <hi>A 1,</hi> one of the parts giuen, then laying a ruler on <hi>A,</hi> and <hi>V,</hi> it will cut <hi>S 3</hi> in <hi>T,</hi> the line <hi>3 T</hi> is ſo often contained in <hi>3 S</hi> as <hi>1 A</hi> is contained in <hi>A 2:</hi> and ſo in both caſes you haue cut off from the line gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the part which was required.</p>
                     <div type="corollary">
                        <head>A Corollary.</head>
                        <p>IF any proportion giuen in a right line as the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is betwéene <hi>1, 2</hi> and <hi>2 A,</hi> you may in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner finde in any line giuen, for both <hi>W Y</hi> is to <hi>X Y</hi> and <hi>S T</hi> to <hi>T 3,</hi> as <hi>2, 1,</hi> is to <hi>1 A.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:13856:42"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:13856:42"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:13856:43"/>
                        <p>
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="corollary">
                        <head>Another Corollary.</head>
                        <p>IN like manner you may inlarge, or contract any Scale at pleaſure: firſt taking the halfe, third, fourth or what part elſe you will of it, by this probleme, and then againe diuide that part ſo taken into the parts whereinto the Scale is diuided, and by this Scale ſo contracted you may make a plat, whoſe ſides correſpondent to the ſides of the firſt plat, ſhall be halfe or a third or a fourth part, or any number you firſt tooke, likewiſe by the ſecond caſe you may enlarge them at your pleaſure.</p>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:13856:43"/>
                        <p>You may alſo diuide any line giuen into more parts then are in the ſide <hi>A B,</hi> which how to performe with ſome cautions for auoyding error in mechanicall practiſe, I will reſerue till another edition.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. 3. Of the Meridian line, the variation of the Compaſſe and the height of the Pole.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>A lemma</hi> About a Circle giuen to deſcribe a Quadrant.</head>
                     <p>LEt the Circle giuen be <hi>B C D E,</hi> whoſe center let be <hi>A,</hi> and let the Diameters <hi>B D, C E</hi> be perpendicular one to another, then extending one of them, namely <hi>B D,</hi> make <hi>A G</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>B C,</hi> vpon <hi>G</hi> as a Center at the diſtance <hi>G B,</hi> deſcribe an arch <hi>F B H,</hi> and from <hi>G</hi> draw two touch lines <hi>G L F,</hi> and <hi>G M H:</hi> I ſay that <hi>G F H</hi> is a Quadrant, circumſcribed about the circle <hi>B C D E, vz.</hi> the lines <hi>F G, G H,</hi> &amp; the circumference <hi>F B H,</hi> do only touch it.</p>
                     <p>If you make the ſemidiameter of the quadrant to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther line, as <hi>D B</hi> the Diameter of any circle giuen, is to the diſtance <hi>B C,</hi> ſubtending a quadrant of the ſame circle, the exceſſe of the Dameter aboue that line, is the ſemidiameter of the circle to be inſcribed in that quadrant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The vſe and making of an inſtrument tractable as well at Sea, as at Land, wherein the ſhadow of the Sunne ſhall at one inſtant poynt out his magneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Azimute and height.</head>
                     <p>VPon the center <hi>A,</hi> deſcribe a circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> and by the former <hi>Lemma,</hi> about it deſcribe a Quadrant <hi>G F H:</hi> and draw the lines <hi>A L, A M</hi> parallell to the ſides <hi>F G,</hi> and <hi>G H,</hi> then diuide the lymbe <hi>F B H</hi> into <hi>90.</hi> degrées, beginning at <hi>F,</hi> this being done, cut out a circle ſomewhat
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13856:44"/>leſſe then the circle <hi>B C D E,</hi> but concentricke vnto it. Then take an <hi>Iſoſcheles</hi> triangle <hi>G H O;</hi> hauing the angle at <hi>H</hi> aright angle, and either the ſides including it equall to the ſemidiameter of the Quadrant, this triangle muſt be placed vpon the line <hi>G H,</hi> in ſuch manner, as the poynt <hi>G</hi> agrée iuſt with the center of the quadrant, and ſo that the plaines of the quadrant and traingle be perpendicular one to the other: then muſt there in ſome place of the line <hi>F G</hi> be ſet a ſtanderd or plate (it will be beſt betwéene <hi>L</hi> and <hi>G</hi>) ſo that one of the edges ſtanding iuſt vpon the line <hi>G F,</hi> be perpendicular vnto it, and the whole plate it ſelfe parallell to the forenamed rectangle triangle. On this ſtandard, or ſome where in the triangle on that ſide, which reſpecteth <hi>F,</hi> you muſt hang a plumbe line, and if you will ſet another plate vpon <hi>F G,</hi> ſome where about <hi>F,</hi> making his ſection with the quadrant in the line <hi>G F,</hi> and alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular vnto the plaine of the quadrant, you may by a plumbe line hanged vpon this plate, or ſtandard, and the other plumbe line holde the quadrant <hi>G F H,</hi> both at Sea and Land preciſelie leuell with the Horizon. Beſides this you muſt make a round boxe, hauing the circle in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome diuided into <hi>360</hi> degrées, or euery quadrant into <hi>90,</hi> as you like beſt, which boxe muſt be faſtened vnto the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant in ſuch manner, as the two Diameters croſſing one another at right angles, haue the one, one end directly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the poynt <hi>L,</hi> &amp; the other another end likewiſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely anſwering the point <hi>M;</hi> in the center of this bore, you muſt ſet a pinne to beare a néedle touched with a very good Loadſtone, making the néedle of ſuch length, as it may fréely play in the boxe; this bore muſt be couered with a glaſſe to kéepe it from duſt and other hurt, as in dials and compaſſes is vſed. The ſtandards and the triangle may be ſo ſhouldered to the quadrant, that you may take them off, and put them on when you will; the manner how, I néed not to ſtand vpon, euery workeman can eaſily deuiſe how, and alſo ſupplie euery particular circumſtance in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13856:44"/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                        </figure> of this inſtrument required, which I very willinglie referre to their handines and ſkill, onely I muſt warne them very carefullie to place the triangle preciſely perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular to the quadrant, with the poynt of the acute angle agréeing with the center, and that the endes of the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters in the bottome of the boxe, doe very exactly reſpect the poynts <hi>L</hi> and <hi>M</hi> in the ſides of the quadrant, you ſhall vſe this inſtrument thus. Holde the quadrant by the plumbe lines leuell with the Horizon, and turne the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle towards the Sunne, till the ſhadowe of the plate or Standard that is next <hi>G,</hi> doe fall preciſely vpon the line <hi>G F,</hi> or (if you will place it ſo) vpon ſome line parallell vnto it, the ſhadowe in the lymbe of the quadrant will cut off, accounting from <hi>F</hi> vnto it, a circumference equall to the height of the Sunne. At the ſame time if you marke the poynt <hi>M,</hi> and the circumference that is betwéene it and the South ende of the néedle, that is the diſtance of the Sunne from the South of the Magnet, or the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall Azimute of the Sunne reckoned from the South.</p>
                  </div>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13856:45"/>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>By the inſtrument now deſcribed, at noone tyde in any Countrey to finde the Meridian line, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of the Compaſſe, and (hauing the Sunnes declination giuen) the height of the Pole.</head>
                     <p>ALthough it be a matter not very eaſie to finde pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely when it is noone, or the Sunne at the hyeſt, yet may you geſſe when it commeth ſomwhat néere it, as it is commonly practiſed by Sea-men, which vſe at that time with their Aſtrolabe or croſſe ſtaffe, to make foure or fiue ſundry obſeruations, and amongſt them take the hieſt for the Meridian height: in like manner when it draweth to be about nooue, make ſundrie obſeruations with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, marking the height of the Sunne, and his Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neticall Azimute, as was euen now ſhewed in the vſe of the inſtrument, the greateſt height is the Meridian height, and the Diameter <hi>A M</hi> doth preciſely anſwere the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an line, the circumference intercepted betwéene it and the ſouth poynt of the néedle, is the variation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, whether Eaſt of Weſt, is eaſilie determined by the ſide of <hi>A M,</hi> on which the néedle reſteth. Now the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an height being giuen, with the declination, you haue been taught in the tenth Concluſion of the ſecond Section, how to finde the Latitude or height of the Pole. The common manner of finding it by adding or ſubtracting of the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is more artificiallie handled by <hi>Nonnius lib. 2. cap. 9. de Reg. Nauig.</hi> then hath to my knowledge béen hitherto publiſhed in Engliſh, and therfore I thinke it not amiſſe to tranſlate his words, which be thus:</p>
                     <p>We muſt obſerue the ſunne, when he is higheſt aboue the Horizon, which is at noone, then if the ſhadowes of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies perpendicular to the Horizon be caſt that away, that the Sunne declineth, in the day of your obſeruation, you muſt adde the complement of his greateſt height to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:13856:45"/>ſo haue you the degrées and minutes of the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, North, if the Sunnes declination be North, South, if it be South.</p>
                     <p>But if the ſhadowes be caſt to the contrarie part, then you muſt compare the Sunnes declination with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of his height, which if you finde equall, the Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith is in the Equinoctiall: but if they be vnequall, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the leſſe from the greater, &amp; the remainder is the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, named of the declination, if the declination be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but if leſſe, of the contrarie part or ſide.</p>
                     <p>When the ſunne hath no declination, the complement of his greateſt height is the latitude, and toward that part or pole, towards which the ſhadowes are caſt: you may know by the Mariners Compaſſe whether the ſhadowes be caſt North or South. When the Sunne is in the Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith, the declination, if it haue any, is the latitude: thus much <hi>Nonnius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>By the ſame inſtrument two obſeruations being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; when the Sun hath equall altitudes, to finde the Meridian line, the variation of the compaſſe, and (the Sunnes declination beeing giuen) the height of the Pole.</head>
                     <p>THe Sunne doth not alwaies ſhine at noone, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at other times you may helpe your ſelfe thus. Make an obſeruation with your inſtrument marking the height of the Sunne, and the circumference intercepted by the point of the néedle, and that diameter, which is perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular to that ſide of the quadrant, on which the triangle ſtandeth, and doe this if you will foure or fiue times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone: in the after noone marke, when the Sun com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth againe to the ſame height, which it had anie time, when you made your obſeruations in the forenoone, and againe how many degrées are betwéene the Diameter
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13856:46"/>that is perpendicular to the ſide of the Triangle, and the North point of the néedle, then compare that found in the fore noone, with that you found in the afternoone: if they be both on the ſame ſide of the néedle, ſubtract the leſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the greater, and the halfe of the reſidue pointeth forth the right North, to which if you adde the exceſſe of the greater magneticall Azimute aboue the leſſe, you haue the variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Compaſſe, Eaſtward, if the firſt obſeruation were leſt, Weſtward, if the ſecond. But if the one be on the one ſide, and the other on the other, then adde both the circumferences together, &amp; of them both take the half, that point determineth the preciſe north: with this halfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the laſt obſeruation, and if it be greater, the variati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Eaſtward, but Weſtward if it be leſſe. Now the Meridian line being found, you know the Azimute, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Sunne was at the time of your obſeruation, and you alſo tooke his height, which two being giuen with his declination, you may finde the latitude, as was ſhewed in the <hi>8</hi> and <hi>10</hi> concluſions of the ſecond Section.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>By the ſame inſtrument three obſeruations beeing taken, whereof two bee, when the Sunne hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall altitudes, to finde the Meridian line, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of the Compaſſe, the declination of the Sunne, and the height of the Pole.</head>
                     <p>YOur thrée obſeruations being taken as is required, you haue two of them when the Sunnes heights be equall, by which you are taught in the former probleme how to finde the Meridian line, and the variation of the Compaſſe, the Meridian line being found, you may knowe the diſtance of both thoſe Azimutes from it, which haue different Altitudes, by which two Azimutes and their altitudes, the ninth and tenth Concluſions of the ſecond Section wil ſhew you, how to finde the declination of the Sunne, and the Latitude.</p>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:13856:46"/>
                     <p>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>By the ſame inſtrument three obſeruations being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken howſoeuer, to finde the Meridian line, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of the Compaſſe, the declination of the Sunne, and the height of the Pole.</head>
                     <p>HAuing taken by your inſtrument in thrée obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the heights and diſtances of their Azimutes:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13856:47"/>from any quarter of the lymbe, whoſe Diameter you muſt account for the firſt Azimute, number the diſtance of the ſecond, and from that poynt ſo taken, the diſtance of the third, and let thoſe poynts of the Azimutes be <hi>E F G,</hi> drawe the lines <hi>F A, G A;</hi> againe, let <hi>E H</hi> be the height be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Azimute <hi>E,</hi> and <hi>E K</hi> the height for the Azi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mute <hi>F,</hi> and <hi>E N</hi> the height for the Azimute <hi>G;</hi> now laying a ruler vpon <hi>B</hi> and <hi>H,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>I,</hi> againe laying a ruler on <hi>B</hi> and <hi>K,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>L,</hi> in <hi>A F</hi> make <hi>A M</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to <hi>A L,</hi> againe laying a ruler on <hi>B</hi> and <hi>N,</hi> it will cut <hi>A E</hi> in <hi>O,</hi> in <hi>A G</hi> take <hi>A P</hi> equall to <hi>A O,</hi> now vnto the thrée poynts <hi>I, M, P,</hi> finde the center, which let be <hi>Q,</hi> on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Q</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the lymbe in <hi>R,</hi> that point <hi>R</hi> is the right North, or South, and ſo haue you the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Azimutes from it, that is <hi>E R</hi> is the diſtance of the firſt, <hi>F R</hi> of the ſecond, <hi>G R</hi> of the third, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of theſe Azimutes, and the Magneticall Azimute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to euery of them, is the variation of the Compaſſe: by any two of theſe Azimutes, ſo their height be different, in the ſecond Section you are taught to finde the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and height of the Pole, which two things in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme required, <hi>Nonnius,</hi> from whom thus much is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, <hi>Lib. 2. Nauig. c. 16.</hi> proſecuteth after a farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent manner, yet ſutable to the conſtruction here ſet down alreadie: but for that his conſtruction will ſeldome be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within the compaſſe of the lymbe, I thought good to omit it: this finding of the Meridian line, being very inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and commodious, though it ſometime will incurre the like inconuenience, I thought worthie to be knowne. <hi>Clauius</hi> hath another way to performe the things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but nothing eaſier then this of <hi>Nonnius.</hi> For both of them aboute the Equinoctiall will produce the conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hugely without the compaſſe of the lymbe, and in <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his way, the Sunnes parallell will differ little from a right line, ſo that you muſt vſe a peculiar inſtrument for to deſcribe it, and yet are you nothing the nearer for fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13856:47"/>of the center. Therfore if at Sea the Azimutes and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micanters of the Starres might be taken, <hi>Nonnius</hi> his conſtruction would be of farre more vſe: for then work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ſuch ſtars as be neare the Poles, their Parallelles would eaſily be deſcribed. I haue thought of an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for that purpoſe, as to vſe a quadrant with an index, and ſights, inſteade of the triangle, or to fit your boxe with the needle, at the lower end of the Marriners Aſtrolabe, for want of experience I dare not affirme much, but I think that Arte, handineſſe, and diligence might doe ſome thing with ſuch inſtruments, the better conſideration whereof, I willinglie referre to the Seamans experience.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Sunnes declination beeing giuen with the height of the pole, to finde the Meridian line by one obſeruation.</head>
                     <p>PLacing your quadrant with the triangle vppon anie plaine made leuell with the Horizon, turne it as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the finding of the height, and by the ſide, on which your ſtandardes are placed, drawe a right line: by the height, which you then finde, in a countrie of knowne Latitude the Sunnes declination beeing giuen, you are taught in the ſecond ſection Concluſion <hi>13,</hi> to find the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimute, which being done, deſcribe a circle vppon a center taken in the former line, and from the line taking accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly a circumference anſwering the Azimute, the line which ioyneth that point, and the center, is the Meridian line. <hi>Clauius</hi> hath two other waies to do this: one <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. lib. 1. cap. 23.</hi> the other in his Aſtrolabe <hi>lib. 3. Can. 12.</hi> and a third I haue found, but none to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which is here propounded, notwithſtanding if this booke bee printed againe, thoſe thrée alſo ſhall bée adioyned.</p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:13856:48"/>
                     <p>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. 4. Of Mappes or Chartes and Nauticall directions.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Anie line being giuen, to finde another line, vnto which the line giuen ſhall haue that proportion, that the Meridian hath to any Parallell.</head>
                     <p>VPon the center <hi>G</hi> deſcribe a ſemicircle <hi>F H Y,</hi> and let <hi>H G</hi> be perpendicular to <hi>F Y.</hi> Let <hi>F B, Y Z</hi> be equall to the diſtance of the Parallell from the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctiall, and draw the lines <hi>B G, G Z:</hi> let <hi>G A</hi> be equall to the line giuen, and in <hi>G Z</hi> take <hi>G S,</hi> equall to <hi>G A,</hi> laying a ruler on <hi>A,</hi> and <hi>S,</hi> it will cut <hi>G H</hi> in <hi>M,</hi> drawe the line <hi>A M.</hi> I ſay <hi>G A,</hi> or the line giuen hath the ſame proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>A M,</hi> that the Meridian hath to the Parallell, whoſe diſtance from the Equinoctial is <hi>F B,</hi> which was required to be giuen. I thought good to ſet downe this exacte and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13856:48"/>readie way, becauſe that, which <hi>Mercator</hi> deſcribeth in the proeme of his reformed tables for <hi>Ptolomey,</hi> is more troubleſome, and leſſe exact.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To deuide any line, or the ſide of your quadrant, or your ruler as that line is deuided, which in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard Mercators</hi> Generall mappe, and his directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium doth anſwere the Meridian.</head>
                     <p>DEuide the line you take for the ground of this worke firſt into <hi>10</hi> equal parts, and then euery one into fiue parts, imagining euerie one of the fift partes to be deuided into twentie: beſides take euerie fift part for a degrée in longitude: then to finde the degrées of latitude anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto it doe thus: in <hi>G Y</hi> the ſemidiameter of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant <hi>GH Y</hi> take <hi>G I</hi> equall to one degrée of longitude, and by <hi>I,</hi> draw the line <hi>I P</hi> parallell to <hi>G H;</hi> then laying a ruler on <hi>G</hi> and euery degrée of the limbe, accounting from <hi>Y</hi> marke where it cutteth <hi>I P,</hi> the line intercepted betwéene thoſe ſections and <hi>G</hi> doe anſwere the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent degrée: as for example, I take a degrée at <hi>Z, vz.</hi> the <hi>45</hi> degrée, then I lay a ruler on <hi>G</hi> and <hi>Z,</hi> which cutteth <hi>I P</hi> in <hi>2,</hi> the line <hi>G 2</hi> in the Meridian anſwereth the point <hi>Z,</hi> or is the <hi>45</hi> degrée: Now hauing marked theſe ſections for euerie degrée in the quadrant, tranſfer them one after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother into your ruler, or the ſide of your quadrant, that is at one end of your quadrant, take a line equall to that, which anſwereth one degrée, adde to it, that which anſwereth the ſecond, to that put that, which anſwereth the third, and ſo till you come to the end of that line, which not being able to receiue all, draw another line, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the like conſtruction in that, and ſo in the third, and forth till you haue tranſferred all the lines anſwering your degrées. If in this tranſferring, your deuiſions agrée not iuſt with the ends of your lines, you muſt take onelie the ouerplus of the laſt deuiſion in the beginning of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13856:49"/>next line, and ſo procéed as is aforeſaid. Now hauing your lines thus deuided, and another deuided to the ſame parts that the ſide of your quadrant is, being parallell to them, &amp; all perpendicular to one right line, you may readilie know what equall partes are contained betwéene any two of your degrées taken howſoeuer, whereby you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all the vſes of <hi>Mercators Directorium.</hi> Thus for example.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Longitudes and Latitudes of any two places being giuen, to finde their direction, commonlie called the Rumbe.</head>
                     <p>TAke the equall parts contained, as well in the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the latitudes, as in the diffrence of their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudes, and ſee whether both be leſſe then the ſide of your quadrant, or no: firſt ſuppoſe they be leſſe, and let the gea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be <hi>X G,</hi> the leſſer <hi>G M:</hi> draw the line <hi>X M,</hi> deuide <hi>G X</hi> into two equall parts in <hi>V,</hi> then opening your Compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>V G,</hi> and kéeping one foote in <hi>V,</hi> with the other marke <hi>T,</hi> in <hi>M X;</hi> on <hi>T</hi> and <hi>G</hi> laying a ruler, it will cut the limbe in <hi>4.</hi> Now if the difference of the Latitudes be leſſe then the difference of the longitudes, <hi>4 Y</hi> is the diſtance of the rumbe from the Meridian, but if the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the longitudes be leſſe, then is <hi>4 P</hi> the diſtance of the rumbe from the Meridian. But now ſuppoſe that one or both the differences, be greater then the ſide of your quadrant, then by the rule of proportions, you muſt finde a line, vnto which the leſſer is, as the greater is to the ſide of the quadrant, or make the ſide of the quadrant to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther line, as the greater is to the leſſer, namelie let <hi>G Y</hi> be vnto <hi>G Q,</hi> as the greater difference is to the leſſe, and draw the line <hi>Q Y:</hi> deuide <hi>G Y</hi> into two equall partes in <hi>W,</hi> then opening your Compaſſe to the diſtance <hi>W G,</hi> and kéeping one foote in <hi>W,</hi> in <hi>Y Q</hi> marke <hi>R,</hi> a ruler laid on <hi>G</hi> and <hi>R,</hi> will cut the limbe in <hi>3:</hi> now as before, if the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13856:49"/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                        </figure> of the longitudes be the greater, then is <hi>H 3</hi> the diſtance of the rumbe from the Meridian, South, if the place reſpected be South, North, if it be North, and ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Eaſt, or Weſt.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:13856:50"/>
                  <head>CHAP. 5. Of the backe of your plate.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To inſcribe in the backe of your plate the fixed ſtars according to their Longitudes and Latitudes, or declinations and right aſcenſions, as you pleaſe.</head>
                     <p>LEt the vtter edge of the backe ſide of your plate be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into <hi>360</hi> degrées, which you may vſe for the Zodiacke, or the Equinoctiall; the Zodiacke, if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Starres according to their Longitudes and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, or the Equinoctiall, if you will place them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their declinations and right aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions, which is the beſt, for thoſe are oftneſt in vſe, both are done after one manner thus. From the beginning of <hi>Aries</hi> reckon the right aſcenſion, as from <hi>E</hi> by <hi>B</hi> vnto <hi>T,</hi> and draw the line <hi>A T,</hi> then from <hi>B</hi> to <hi>V,</hi> reckon the declination <hi>B V,</hi> laying a ruler on <hi>V</hi> and <hi>A,</hi> it will cut the Synicall arch of the limbe <hi>A S C,</hi> in <hi>S,</hi> in the lyne <hi>A T</hi> take <hi>A Q</hi> equall to the diſtance <hi>A S,</hi> and the point <hi>Q</hi> is the place of the ſtarre ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his right aſcenſion and declination: this being done, ſet downe by it the name, and <hi>S</hi> or <hi>N,</hi> to ſignifie, whether it decline North, or South. This may be done ſo ſleightlie, that you may rub it out when you will with a wet pumice, and yet déepe enough to continue a great while for your vſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To finde the longitude and latitude, or the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and right aſcenſion of ſuch ſtars as bee pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the back of the plate.</head>
                     <p>VPon the center of the plate, and the point of the ſtar lay a ruler, where it cutteth the limbe, is the right aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion reckoned from the vernall Section, or the longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, if they be placed for the Zodiacke. As for example:
<pb facs="tcp:13856:50"/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>sky chart</figDesc>
                           <head>Place this figure in ſteade of the figure in folio <hi>35.</hi>
                           </head>
                        </figure>
                        <pb facs="tcp:13856:51"/>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:13856:51"/>lay a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>Q,</hi> it will cut the limbe in <hi>T,</hi> the circumference <hi>E B T</hi> is the right aſcenſion of <hi>Q.</hi> Now if in <hi>A S C</hi> the Synicall arch of the limbe, you applie from <hi>A</hi> to <hi>S,</hi> a diſtance equall to <hi>A Q,</hi> and lay a ruler on <hi>A</hi> and <hi>S,</hi> it will cut the limbe in <hi>V,</hi> the circumference <hi>B V</hi> is the declination of the ſtarre placed at <hi>Q,</hi> or the latitude, if they were placed according to the longitudes, &amp; latitudes: by the letter <hi>S</hi> or <hi>N</hi> you ſhall know whether it bee North, or ſouth. And that you may be furniſhed for theſe two laſt problemes, I haue ſet downe on the other ſide a table out of <hi>Clauius,</hi> contayning certaine fixed ſtarres, both with their longitudes and latitudes, and their declinations and right aſcenſions, calculated for this yeare <hi>1600.</hi> And thus much at this time, for the Planiſphere, which hereafter I meane to increaſe with more concluſions, &amp; problemes, and could haue now enlarged it with handling menſurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Synicall calculations and dialling: but thoſe thinges ſéemed ſomewhat farre from my principall purpoſe, and therefore I will intreate the reader to accept thus much onely as now is deliuered, and ſo for this time I end.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>The end of the new handling of the Planiſphere.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:52"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A Table of fixed Starres out of <hi>Cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ius,</hi> calculated for the yeere 1600. compleat.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Bignes</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Names.</cell>
                     <cell role="label" cols="3">Place in the Zo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diacke or Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gitude</cell>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">Their Lati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude</cell>
                     <cell role="label">The part</cell>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">The de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clinati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">The part.</cell>
                     <cell role="label" cols="2">The righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>The Rams former horne.</cell>
                     <cell>Aries</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Meduſaes head.</cell>
                     <cell>Taur</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Bulles eye.</cell>
                     <cell>Gem.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Orions right ſhoulder.</cell>
                     <cell>Gem.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>83</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>The Goate.</cell>
                     <cell>Gem.</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>The great dogge.</cell>
                     <cell>Can.</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>97</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Hydraes bright Starre.</cell>
                     <cell>Leo.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>137</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Lions hart.</cell>
                     <cell>Leo.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>146</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Lions tayle.</cell>
                     <cell>Virg.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>171</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>The Virgins ſpike.</cell>
                     <cell>Lib.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>195</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Arcturus.</cell>
                     <cell>Lib.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>209</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Scorpions heart.</cell>
                     <cell>Scor.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>241</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Harpe.</cell>
                     <cell>Cap.</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>275</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Laſt in Aquarius water.</cell>
                     <cell>Aqu:</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>339</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Swannes tayle.</cell>
                     <cell>Piſc.</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>307</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Pegaſus legge.</cell>
                     <cell>Piſc.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell>341</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 3. line vlt. <hi>Analemma.</hi> p. 6. l. 6. <hi>Maurolycus.</hi> p. 10. l. 9. <hi>Friſius.</hi> p. 13. l. vlt. <hi>Motus raptus.</hi> p. 14. l. 33. Zenith, appearing. p. 16. l. 33. from the Zenith, which. p. 17. l. 2.5.7. for Z make L. p. 22. l. 1. blot out pan. and l. 11. N L. p. 23. l 13.25. for Z make L. ibid. l 20 Tropickes. p. 24. l. 26. there mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th angles. p. 25. l. 12. and by two of thoſe. p. 26. l. 9. ſetting Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. p. 32 l. 26.27. for Q make 7. p. 33. l. 10. for 3 &amp; 3: make 8 &amp; 8. ibid. l. 13. for G make E. p. 34 l. 4.5. for T make V. l. 13 for F make E. l. 27. which let be C 1, 1 l, and l K. l.: 8: 29. for B make P. p. 26 l. 2.7. for B make P. l. 5. for 12. make 2. l 8. for 2. and D make P. p. 38. l. 18. and H l, cutting. p. 40. l. 23. for K make B. in the figure of the 39. page place 3. on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of D.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13856:52"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
